<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of France in its several governments together with the most considerable cities, sea-ports, and rivers of that kingdom; as also the distances, with the longitudes, and latitudes of each place, &amp;c. with many other remarks, necessary to the knowledge of that kingdom. By J.S. Gent. Illustrated with a map.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S51</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212956</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825520</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2132:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of France in its several governments together with the most considerable cities, sea-ports, and rivers of that kingdom; as also the distances, with the longitudes, and latitudes of each place, &amp;c. with many other remarks, necessary to the knowledge of that kingdom. By J.S. Gent. Illustrated with a map.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
                  <author>Hove, Frederick Hendrick van, 1628?-1698, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 124 p., folded plate : map  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Minors in the Inner-Temple-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The map is signed: F.H. van. Hove sculp.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The geographical description of France.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Description and travel --  1600-1799 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DESCRIPTION OF FRANCE IN ITS Several Governments: TOGETHER With
the moſt conſiderable Cities, Sea-Ports, and Rivers of that Kingdom; as
alſo the Diſtances, with the Longitudes, and Latitudes of each Place,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> With many other Remarks, neceſſary to the Knowledge of
that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. S.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Illuſtrated with a Map.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Minors</hi> in the
<hi>Inner-Temple-Lane,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:29904:2"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date> 
                     <hi>July</hi> the <hi>18th.</hi>
1692.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>R. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29904:2"/>
            <head>To the Illuſtrious <hi>Mainard</hi> Duke of
<hi>Leinſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Treatiſe would not be ſo fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, as to
preſume upon ſo high a Patronage, were not your Grace ſo imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
intereſſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein. Neither was it without ſome ſerious
Reſlexion and Debate, that I could reſolve to make this Preſent to your
Grace: For though Dedications are lately grown ſo Epidemical, that no
Perſon of Quality, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb facs="tcp:29904:3"/>ſooner or later can avoid the
Infection, yet, methought, your Grace was as much above the common
diſturbances that attend your Quality, as you are exalted above the common
Level of it. But, my Lord, you are now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing General of an Expedition, in
whoſe very Name encounter an admirable Policy, and a certain Glory; for the
Service of which was principally intended this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Deſcription. This
it is which made me conclude I ſhould have done a great Injuſtice, had I
put this Tract under any other Protection than yours. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at whoſe
Feet can a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Nature be ſo fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly placed as at your Grace's,
You being ſo experienc'd a Commander, and about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <pb facs="tcp:29904:3"/>ſuch vaſt important Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <p>My Lord, it would but ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue me of the meaneſt Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence to
pretend here an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue of thoſe Encomiums you deſerve: For he who
acquaints the World whoſe Son you are, has ſaid enough to thoſe who do
not know you: Your Grace being the beſt Panegyrick upon your ſelf: The Son
of the Great, the Immortal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> whoſe ſtupendious Actions,
and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Courage, together with his unſpotted Zeal for the most
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Religion of the World, at a time when the Thorns of Perſecution
forced him from his Eſtate and Dignities, have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him even above the
<hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennee's,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:29904:4"/>the <hi>Montecuculli's,</hi> and the
<hi>Condees,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Caeſars</hi> of our Age.</p>
            <p>Go on, my Lord, and proſper; And whilſt your glorious Father's
Blood inheres in you, where's the conſidering Man that queſtions Victory,
ordares diſpute Succeſs.</p>
            <p>Methinks, I hear the Men of <hi>Gaul</hi> declare, amazed upon the
Notice of your Landing, He comes, 'tis <hi>Schomberg</hi>'s Son, why do we
defer to yield?</p>
            <p>We read in Engliſh Hiſtory of the prodigious Actions of the
Mighty <hi>Talbot,</hi> whoſe very Name at laſt was of ſufficient force
to defeat whole Armies: The Caſe being parallel to the great Exploits of your
Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb facs="tcp:29904:4"/>Father, of whom your Grace is a compleat Reſemblance,
how can it be, that we ſhould fear a Victory?</p>
            <p>The Preſent that I make bold to ſend your Grace, is a
Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical Deſcription of <hi>France,</hi> conſidered in its ſeveral
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, the moſt conſiderable Cities and Sea Ports, their Diſtances
one from another, their Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and Latitudes, what they are moſt
remarkable for, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with many other obſervable things, that
neceſſarily occur in a Treatiſe of this Nature.</p>
            <p>But leſt I prove tedious, I will conclude this Epiſtle with
aſſuring you, that not only this Book, but the Author of it are <pb facs="tcp:29904:5"/>both Dedicated to your Grace's Service, (with hearty Prayers for the
Succeſs of your Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) by him, who in all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Humility,
ſubſcribes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord, </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Grace's Moſt Obedient
Servant</hi> J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 25. line 19. after <hi>Beſanſon</hi> read and
<hi>Cambray;</hi> p. 27. l. 15 for <hi>Boulonis</hi> r. <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonois.</hi> p.
35. l. 4. r. <hi>Vexin Normand.</hi> p. 37. l. 23. before King r. the, and l.
26. for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment r. Governour. p. 47. l. 8. for <hi>Rhetelor</hi> r.
<hi>Rhetelois.</hi> p. 52. for <hi>Bree</hi> r. <hi>La Brie.</hi> p. 57. l. 10.
for more r. moſt. p. 58. l. 19. r. Families. p. 61. l. 10. r.
<hi>Poitou.</hi> p. 65. l. 11. r. <hi>Bretagne.</hi> p. 66. l. 1. r. covered
with Slat. p. 83. l. 14. r. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rente</hi> and l. 26. after
<hi>Guyenne</hi> r. is. p. 90. l. 3. after Modern r. Authors. p. 93. l. 2. r.
advancing p. 101. l. 14. r. It ſhould not be. p. 108. l. 5. r. in one part p.
109. l. 18 after <hi>Ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſin</hi> r. which encircles. p. 112. l. 1 r. moſt. p. 115.
l. 9. r. <hi>Roman.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:29904:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29904:6"/>
            <p> 
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of France.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29904:6"/>
            <head>AN INTRODUCTION TO THE Geographical Deſcription OF
FRANCE.</head>
            <p>THE Romans gave the Name of <hi>Gaul</hi> to that extent of Land,
which is between the <hi>Alpes</hi> and the <hi>Pyrenaeans,</hi> the
<hi>Mediterranean</hi>-Sea, the Ocean, and the <hi>Rhine:</hi> At preſent,
with an exception of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and ſome other Parts, which
do as it were depend upon the Empire of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> it is called
<hi>France,</hi> from the Name of the <hi>French,</hi> who made it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29904:7"/>to their Power. <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> had finiſhed his
Conqueſt of it about Forty Eight Years before the Nativity of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt; inſomuch that when the French had abſolutely eſtabliſhed
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therein, it had been near Five A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges under the Laws of that
Empire.</p>
            <p>Now without reckoning the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try which the <hi>Gauls</hi> had
ſubdued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Alps,</hi> from theſe Mountains, as far as the
little River of <hi>Rubicon,</hi> and which was named <hi>Ciſalpine
Gaul,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Romans: It was firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by
<hi>Auguſtus</hi> into Four Parts, <hi>Narbonoiſe Gaul,</hi> which they
called <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> becauſe they had ſubdued it firſt, and reduced
it into a Province; <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanick Gaul, Gaul Celtick,</hi> and <hi>Gaul
Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick.</hi> To theſe three laſt, they gave the Name of <hi>Gaul
Cheveliie,</hi> and when <hi>Gaul</hi> was abſolutely ſpoken,
<hi>Celtick</hi> was underſtood. Then by Succeſſion of time, and under
divers Emperors, it was divided again into Seventeen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, to wit, Five
<hi>Viennoiſes,</hi> in which number were computed the Firſt and Second
<hi>Narbonoiſe;</hi> Three <hi>Aquitains;</hi> Five <hi>Lyonnoiſes,</hi>
comprehending the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanoiſe;</hi> Four <hi>Belgick,</hi> Two of which
were called <hi>German,</hi> becauſe ſome People <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29904:7"/>of
<hi>Germany</hi> had long ſince inhabited thoſe parts; and Two
<hi>Belgick,</hi> proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called.</p>
            <p>Each of theſe Provinces had its Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis; to wit, the Five
<hi>Viennoiſe, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna, Narbonne, Aix, Tarentaiſe,</hi> and
<hi>Embrun;</hi> the Three <hi>Aquitains, Bourges, Bourdeaux</hi> and
<hi>Eaulſe;</hi> the Five <hi>Lyon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noiſes, Lyon, Rouën, Tours, Sens,
Beſancon;</hi> The Two <hi>German, Mentz</hi> and <hi>Cologne;</hi> the Two
<hi>Belgick, Triers</hi> and <hi>Rheims.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under theſe Seventeen Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, there was above a Hundred
Cities or Towns, Heads of People, in which the Church has ſince conſtituted
Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Sees. Under theſe Cities, there was a much greater number of
other Towns, which they called <hi>Oppida.</hi> When the Romans conquered
<hi>Gaul,</hi> there was no leſs computed than Twelve Hundred with Walls; but
they pulled down the Encloſures of the greateſt part, or let them fall to
ruin.</p>
            <p>As to the Governments of theſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen Provinces, Six of them
were Conſular, and Eleven under Preſidents, commiſſioned by the
Emperor. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Great, put Counts into the Cities, and
Dukes into ſome of the Frontier Towns; Judiciary matters <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29904:8"/>were performed according to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Law, but ſome Municipal
Cuſtoms it's probable were kept up. They were not much diſturbed by the
Soldiery, becauſe the Legions lived with ſufficient order, and beſides
there was hardly any but in the Adjacent Provinces. Yet as the Country was
agreeable and fertile, and the People extreamly ſubject, they were impoſed
upon by all manner of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, inſomuch that their Abundance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> encreaſed their Miſery, and
their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience heigthned their Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>In the Year 330, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great divided the
Charge of <hi>Prefe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du
Pretoire</hi> into Four, <hi>Gaul</hi> enjoyed one, who had under him Three
Vicars one in <hi>Gaul</hi> it ſelf, one in <hi>Spain,</hi> and one in
<hi>Great Britain.</hi> The Firſt who had this Charge, was the Father of St.
<hi>Ambroſe,</hi> bearing the ſame Name as his Son. This Praefect uſually
reſided in the City of <hi>Triers,</hi> which for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was the
Capital of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> till having been Four times ſack'd by the
Barbarians, the Emperor <hi>Honorius</hi> would transfer this Prerogative to
the City of <hi>Arles;</hi> which was at length taken off from <hi>Vienna,</hi>
and made up the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Metropolis.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29904:8"/>
            <p>From <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to <hi>Galien,</hi> the Peace of theſe
Provinces was diſturbed by. Two Revolts that of <hi>Sacrovir</hi> and
<hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> in the Twenty Third Year of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and that of
<hi>Civilis, Tutor &amp; Claſſicus,</hi> which was much more dangerous in
the Year 70. After the Death of the Emperor <hi>Decius,</hi> the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians
began to torment them by frequent Incurſions. For the Firſt Hundred Years
there were none but French and Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans that were concerned in them on this
ſide the <hi>Rhine;</hi> but afterwards the Misfortune was redoubled by the
hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Devaſtations of Vandals, Bourguig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Sueves, Viſigoths and
Huns, which did not end but with the ruin of the Empire in the Weſt.</p>
            <p>As to the Original of the French, the common opinion is, that they
are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Germans, and that <hi>France</hi> is the name of a League, which
in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſignified <hi>Free,</hi> or as others ſay, <hi>Fierce,
Inſuperable.</hi> 'Tis certain that the Authors of the Third and Fourth Ages
by the name of <hi>German,</hi> almoſt always mean the <hi>French.</hi> As
for the time in which they began to appear, it was exactly Two Years after the
great Defeat of the Emperor <hi>Decius</hi> in <hi>Meſia,</hi> 
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29904:9"/>which happened in the Year 254, by the Goths and other People
of <hi>Seythia,</hi> The Goths had begun to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves known but Twelve
Years before they went out of their own Country, which was <hi>European
Scythia,</hi> between the <hi>Euxin</hi> Sea and the River <hi>Tanais,</hi>) to
ranſack the Provinces of the Empire. They were divided into
<hi>Oſtrogoths</hi> and <hi>Viſigoths;</hi> that is to ſay, according to,
ſome Eaſtern Goths and Weſtern Goths.</p>
            <p>After this Defeat, all the Fences of the Roman Empire being
ruinated on that ſide, there broke out Torrents of all ſorts of Barbarians,
who had not been ſo much as heard of till then. 'Tis for this reaſon
amongſt others, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the French had alſo much of the Behaviors
and Cuſtoms of the Scythians, (as to uſe Darts, to exerciſe Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
&amp;c.) that one is apt to conjecture that they are originally Scythians. But
it is not po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible; and it
would be ſuper uous to ſay of what Place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the Scythians were
Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, and that in a little time they were found Two and Three Hundred
Leagues diſtance from the Country, which they inhabited a little before.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29904:9"/>
            <p>The Firſt time then that there is mention made of them, is in
the Year 256, under the Empire of <hi>Gallus</hi> and <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſian,</hi>
when they paſſed the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine</hi> near <hi>Mentz;</hi> and when <hi>Aurelian</hi> who was
yet but Tribune of a Legion, killed Seven Hundred of them in an Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and
made Three Hundred Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, who were ſold at the publick Sale.</p>
            <p>From this firſt Irruption, to the time when they conquered or
beſought of the Romans the Poſſeſſion of ſome Lands in
<hi>Gaul,</hi> to wit, in the Countries of <hi>Cologne, Leige,</hi> and the
Neighbouring parts, there paſſed near 180 Years, which was in the Year 416.
There was lodged a Party in <hi>Brabant</hi> in the time of <hi>Julian</hi> the
Apoſtate, towards the Year 358; but it is not known, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were
permitted to eſtabliſh themſelves there.</p>
            <p>During theſe Two Ages they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued their Incurſions with
divers Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, always retiring with their Booty into <hi>Germany.</hi>
They poſſeſſed there the moſt part of thoſe Lands which are
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Mein</hi> and the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Weſer</hi> and the
Ocean; ſometimes more, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times leſs extended, according as they 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29904:10"/>were weak or powerful, and as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were preſſed by other Nations, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
by the Germans towards th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mein,</hi> and the Saxons towards th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sea.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt proceeding from a Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which we now call <hi>Holſtein,</hi>
ſeiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon
<hi>Frieſland,</hi> and the Marine part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on this ſide the River <hi>Elbe;</hi> then
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the French
eſtabliſhed themſelves i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gaul,</hi> they ſucceeded in the poſſeſſion of the
greateſt part of thoſe which they had enjoyed beyond the
<hi>Rhine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The French Nation was divided into ſeveral People,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Weſt-Frieſland.</note> Great and<note n="(b)" place="margin">North-Holland.</note> Little <hi>Friſons,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Zeland.</note> 
               <hi>Salians,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Brucheri,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Biſhoprick of
<hi>Oſnaburg.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grivarians,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick
of <hi>Minden.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chamaves,</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Dutchy
of <hi>Weſtphaly.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sicambres,</hi> and<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Heſſe.</note> 
               <hi>Catti:</hi> And it had, as I ſuppoſe,
divers others in its Alliance, and others alſo under its Dominion.</p>
            <p>Oftentimes the Romans went to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault them in their Woods and
Marſhes, and thought to extirpate them Two or Three times, particularly
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; but they repulſed them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29904:10"/>
            <p>They had ſeveral Captains or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, Kings, Princes, Dukes
or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, who had no abſolute Authority but in War.</p>
            <p>Sometimes they ſerved as Stipenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the Romans,
ſometimes became their Subjects; but as ſoon as the time was changed, and
that they found an occaſion to pillage, they ſuppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves no
longer obliged to entertain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Treaties; for which Reaſon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of thoſe times accuſe them of
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, Lying, and Perfidiouſneſs: So that we at this time need not
give our ſelves the trouble of admiring at their Treacherous Practices and
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly Attempts, ſince they have them from their firſt Original, and
ſince they ſeem to be carried on thereto as it were by Natural Inſtinct,
deriving their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Qualities from their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</p>
            <p>The laſt Day of the Year 406, the Alains and Vandals ſeducing
along with them the Bourguignons, the Sueves, and ſeveral other Barbarous
People, paſſed the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and made an irruption into
<hi>Gaul,</hi> which was the moſt furious and ſevere that had been yet
ſeen.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:29904:11"/>
            <p>Theſe Barbarians having ranſacked all the Firſt
<hi>Germany,</hi> and the Second <hi>Belgick,</hi> transferr'd themſelves
into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitain:</hi> In the Year 409, ſome Bands of Vandals and Sueves,
paſſed from thence into <hi>Spain.</hi> Two Years after, the others being
conſternated at the March of <hi>Ataulfe</hi> King of the Viſigoths, who
came from <hi>Haly,</hi> took the ſame Road, and followed them. There
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained notwithſtanding ſome of the Alains in <hi>Dauphine,</hi> and upon
the Banks of the <hi>Loire,</hi> who enjoyed a Succeſſion of Kings for
above Sixty Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but in the end they underwent the Dominion of the
Viſigoths and Bourguignons.</p>
            <p>The Vandals and Sueves ſeized upon <hi>la Galice,</hi> the
Silinges <hi>la Betique,</hi> and the Alains part of <hi>Luſit ania,</hi> and
the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Carthagene.</hi> Sixteen Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Vandals
paſſed into <hi>Africk,</hi> but in the mean time <hi>Vallia</hi> King of
the Viſigoths who fought for the Romans, utterly extirpated the Silinges, and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Alains to that extremity, that being unable to ſubſiſt any
longer by themſelves, they went and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Gunderic</hi> King of
the Vandals. The Sueves maintained themſelves near <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29904:11"/>Two
Ages in Spain; and at length their Kingdom was alſo extinguiſhed by
<hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilgild</hi> King of the Viſigoths in the Year 588.</p>
            <p>All theſe Barbarians were divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeveral Bands or
Parties, who had each their Captain, and made Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Ravages without
intermiſſion. So far they proceeded, that there was ſeen at the ſame
time People of the ſame Nation in Places far remote one from the other, and
in Intereſts direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite.</p>
            <p>In the Year 408 <hi>Stilicon, Honorius</hi>'s Lieutenant, who was
accuſed for intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them, is maſſacred by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of
<hi>Honorius</hi> the Emperor. <hi>Alaric</hi> King of the Viſigoths his good
Friend, to revenge his Death, beſieged the City of <hi>Rome</hi> Three times,
and the laſt takes it by Treaſon, on the Twentieth Day of
<hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the Year 410. About the end of the ſame Year, he died
in <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria,</hi> as he was preparing to paſs into <hi>Africk.
Ataulfe</hi> his Couſin ſucceeded him, and eſpouſed <hi>Placidia</hi>
Siſter of the Emperor <hi>Honorius,</hi> whom he had taken in
<hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 412, <hi>Ataulfe</hi> paſſed into <hi>Gaul
Narbonnoiſe,</hi> and makes himſelf <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29904:12"/>Maſter of
<hi>Narbonne.</hi> He remained there but Three Years. The Count
<hi>Conſtantius</hi> who was ſince Emperor, and married <hi>Placidia</hi>
his Widow, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to go into <hi>Spain,</hi> where he was killed by his
own People in <hi>Barcelone,</hi> towards the Month of <hi>September,</hi> in
the Year 415. They elected <hi>Sigerick</hi> in his Place, and gave him the
ſame entertainment on the Seventh Day. <hi>Vallia</hi> his Succeſſor was
remanded into <hi>Gaul</hi> by <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who gave him the Second
<hi>Aquitain,</hi> with ſome Cities in the adjacent Provinces; amongſt
others, that of <hi>Toulouze,</hi> where he eſtabliſhed his Royal Seat in
the Year 419. But he died in few Months after, and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorick</hi>
ſucceeded him. Under this King, and under <hi>Evaric</hi> or <hi>Eurick,</hi>
the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goths became Maſters of all the Three Aquitaines, and the Two
Narbon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noiſes.</p>
            <p>During the great Revolt of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritime People, to wit, thoſe
upon the Coaſts of <hi>Flanders, Picardy, Normandy,</hi> and
<hi>Bretagne,</hi> which happened in the Year 412, the French being joyned with
them, ſeized upon that part of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Germany,</hi> which was called
<hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puaire,</hi> and the people <hi>Ripuarians</hi> or <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29904:12"/>
               <hi>Ribarols.</hi> The Romans by Treaty or otherwiſe, left them the
free poſſeſſion of it: A little after which, <hi>Faramond</hi> began to
reign. We find in the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of thoſe times, that the French had
enjoyed ſeveral Kings before him, as <hi>Genebaud</hi> and <hi>Alec,</hi> in
the Year 288, who came to <hi>Treves,</hi> to ſue for a Peace of
<hi>Maximilian;</hi> As alſo <hi>Aſcaric</hi> and <hi>Radagaiſe,</hi> in
the Year 307, whom <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> took Priſoners in War, and
expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to Wild Beaſts in the <hi>Arena,</hi> for having taken up
Arms, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Faith given to <hi>Conſtantius</hi> his
Father. In the Year 374, one <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lobaudes,</hi> who being great Maſter of
the Militia, and Count of the Palace of the Emperor <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian,</hi> killed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued <hi>Macrian</hi>
King of the Germans, and rendred many other Services to the Empire. Towards the
Year 378, one <hi>Richemer</hi> who had ſuch another Charge near
<hi>Gratian,</hi> as <hi>Mellobaudes</hi> had. In the Year 382, one
<hi>Priam</hi> or <hi>Priarius,</hi> whom ſome would have to be the Father or
Grandfather of <hi>Fara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond;</hi> beſides <hi>Marcomir</hi> and
<hi>Sunnon,</hi> Brethren in 397, the Firſt of which <hi>Stilicon</hi>
baniſhed into <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcany,</hi> and made the other be Maſſacred by his own 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29904:13"/>Creatures, when he attempted to be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> motion to revenge the
Exile of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brother. And in
the Year 414 or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one
<hi>Theodemer</hi> Son of <hi>Richemer,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had his Head cut off with his mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Aſcila,</hi> for ſome
Undertakings again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
Empire.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the common Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion has always begun to reckon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King's of <hi>France</hi> by
<hi>Faramond,</hi> whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
be becauſe his Predeceſſors had not the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fixed reſidence in <hi>Gaul,</hi> or that he
eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bliſhed Royalty
amongſt the Frenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> In
effect, it ſeems that the Romans ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ſome faſhion ſubdued this Nation, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſince the entertainment of <hi>Marcomir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sunnon,</hi> and
<hi>Theodomer,</hi> they would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> longer permit them to have their Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faramond</hi> began to reign in the Year 418, according to the
common Opinion, a Year very remarkable by a Great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Sun: From
whom to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth, the preſent King of <hi>France,</hi>
are computed no leſs than 65 Kings.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29904:13"/>
            <head>THE Geographical Deſcription OF <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRANCE</hi> then,<note place="margin">Name.</note> which was
here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore called <hi>Gaul,</hi> hath received its Name from that of the
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient People called <hi>Franks,</hi> who came from a part of
<hi>Germany,</hi> to inhabit there in the time of its firſt Kings.</p>
            <p>It is Scituated in the midſt of the Temperate Zone,<note place="margin">Situation.</note> between the Forty Second and Fifty Firſt
Degree of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, extending it ſelf from the Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Degree of
Longitude, to the Twenty Ninth, inſomuch that it may be computed to have 460
Miles Engliſh from South to North, from the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neans</hi> 
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29904:14"/>to <hi>Calais</hi> upon the Channel, and 600 in its
greateſt extent from Eaſt to Weſt,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> from
the point of <hi>Conquet</hi> in <hi>Bretagne</hi> to <hi>Saralbe</hi> in
<hi>Lorrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is bounded in the North by the Channel and the
<hi>Low-Countries;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> in the Eaſt by
<hi>Germany, Suiſſerland, Savoy</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> from which it
is ſeparated by the <hi>Alps;</hi> in the South by the
<hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterrancan</hi> Sea, and the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountains, which
ſeparate it from <hi>Spain;</hi> and in the Weſt by the Ocean.</p>
            <p>The Air is recreative and wholſome;<note place="margin">Quality.</note> the Soil extraordinary Fertile in Corn, Wines,
Fruits and Hemp. One meets there with Delicious Medows, Pleaſant Foreſts,
and moſt agreeable Plains, in which one may obſerve a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of
Cattle and Wild Fowl, as Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Oxen, Sheep and Goats, Stags, Wild-boars,
partridges, Woodcocks, Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Quails, and other Volatils. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Authors,
as <hi>Strabo</hi> and <hi>Botero,</hi> ſpeak of its Mines of Gold and
Silver. If they are rare, thoſe of Iron; Lead, Coals and other Minerals are
frequent enough. There are Quarries of moſt Beautiful Stone and Slat,
exceeding pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for Buildings. Towards the South there are ſeveral
Fountains of Hot and <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29904:14"/>Mineral Waters, very relieving for
many Diſtempers. Upon the Coaſts is made a great quantity of very good
Salt. <hi>Botero</hi> ſays, that <hi>France</hi> produces Four Load-ſtones,
which have the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to attract the Gold and Silver of Strangers: Theſe
Four Load-Stones are Corn, Wine, Salt and Hemp. In a Word, there is all that
can be deſired in order to paſs ones Life after a moſt agreeable
manner.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the great Number of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers which fructify this Country,<note place="margin">Rivers.</note> Four are particularly obſerved, to wit, the
<hi>Loire,</hi> the <hi>Seine,</hi> the <hi>Garomne,</hi> and the
<hi>Rhone;</hi> all of them take their riſe herein; but the laſt, which
proceeds from the Mount St. <hi>Gothard,</hi> in the Country of the
<hi>Griſons,</hi> and paſſes through the Lake of <hi>Geneva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> is divided according to the Twelve great
Governments which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to the General Aſſembly of the States held in
1614,<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> after the majority of <hi>Lewis</hi>
the Thirteenth; but we muſt now make an addition of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and the
French-County, which are in its dependance, ſo that we will divide it in
Fourteen principal parts. Four of theſe Governments, to wit, <hi>Picardy, 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29904:15"/>Normandy,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>France</hi> and
<hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne,</hi> are Situated to the North of the <hi>Loire,</hi> and about
the <hi>Seine,</hi> except the Firſt, which is more Northerly than the other
Three. Thoſe of <hi>Bretagne, Orleanois, Bourgogne,</hi> and
<hi>Lyonois,</hi> are about the <hi>Loire;</hi> and the other Four are to the
South of the ſame River, to wit, <hi>Guyenne</hi> and <hi>Languedoc,</hi>
about the <hi>Garomne, Dauphine</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> to the Eaſt of
the <hi>Rhone,</hi> one towards the North, and the other towards the South.
<hi>Lorrain</hi> and the <hi>French-County</hi> are directly Scituated to the
Eaſt of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Capital City of <hi>France</hi> is <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Capital.</note> ſeated in the midſt of the Iſle of
<hi>France,</hi> upon the River <hi>Seine.</hi> It paſſes for a Vaſt,
Rich and Populous City, one of the Nobleſt in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and a
Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament City, ſubject to the king of <hi>France</hi> and his ordinary
Seat. It is an Archbiſhops See, and is adorned with a Famous univerſity and
Three illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Academies, embeliſhed with a great number of Magni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cent Churches and Stately
Buildings, about Two Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
and Eight Miles almoit S. E. of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The French are full of Spirit,<note place="margin">Manners.</note>
active <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29904:15"/>and ingenious enough in Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, polite
and agreeable in Convrſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, complaiſant to the Ladies, and courteous to
Strangers, but withal very unconſtant, and very raſh, <hi>(ut ſunt
ſubita Gallorum ingenia,)</hi> is one of the Remarks of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> A
French Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was one Day ſpeaking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiouſly of the Free, Genteel
Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of his Countrymen to an Italian, and ſaid, that there was no Nation
could deny, but that the French were the moſt tractable and ſincere People
in the World; to which the Italian an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that the thing from which he
pretended to draw all his Advantages, paſſed with them for a weakneſs,
and an effect of their imprudence. I don't admire, replied the French-man
coldly, that you make ſo diſadvantagious a Judgment of our beſt
Qualities, becauſe your Politicks believe, that without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Cunning
Knave, one can never make a Gallant Man.</p>
            <p>As to the Perſons of this People, they are commonly of a Middle
Stature, and for the moſt part of a ſlight making; their Complexion being
generally hot and moiſt, which makes them very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the heats of
Luſt, and eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29904:16"/>to thoſe Diſeaſes
which are its Concomitants.</p>
            <p>Their chief Exerciſes are Tennis and Dancing;<note place="margin">Exerciſe.</note> to the laſt of which they are ſo generally
affected, that were it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſo much exclaimed againſt by their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid Miniſters, it is thought that
many more of the French Catholicks had been of the Reformed Religion. For ſo
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly are they bent upon this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, that no interruption
whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, neither Age, Sickneſs, nor even Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty ſhall retain their
Heels when they hear the Muſick.</p>
            <p>Their Language is very ſmooth and pleaſant,<note place="margin">Language.</note> but rather Elegant than Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and therefore
much troubled for want of Words to find out Periphraſes; beſides, that a
great deal of it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Action; the head and Shoulders move
as ſignificantly towards it, as the Lips and Tongue; and he that pretends to
ſpeak it with a good grace, muſt have ſomewhat in him of the Buffoon. It
is enriched with variety of Proverbs, which is a great help to the French
Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of Scoffing; a Language ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally diſpoſed for Courtſhip,
as makes all the people Complemental.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29904:16"/>
            <p>The Laws of this Kingdom are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Temporary,<note place="margin">Laws.</note> and alterable at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; or Fundamental, which
neither King nor parliament (as they ſay) can alter. Of this laſt fort, the
Principal are the Salick Law, and the Law of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pennages.</hi> By the Salick
Law the Crown of <hi>France</hi> may not deſcend unto the Females, or fall
from the Launce to the Diſtaff, as their Saying is, which Law one undertaking
to juſtify out of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ, urged that Text of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> where
it is ſaid, <hi>Mark the Lillies,</hi> (which are the Arms of
<hi>France,</hi>) <hi>and ſee how they neither labour nor ſpin.</hi> By
that of the <hi>Apennage,</hi> the younger Sons of the King are not to have a
ſhare in the Kingdom with their Elder brother; which Law was made by
<hi>Charles</hi> the Great, before whoſe time we find the Children of the
Kings ſtated in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Thrones, and the Realm divided amongſt
them into many Kingdoms. But by this Law, they are to be entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſome
Dutchy or County, with all the Rights and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts belonging thereto; all matters of Regality (as
Levying Taxes, Coynage, and the like,) excepted only; which upon the failing of
the Maſculine Line, return again to <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29904:17"/>the Crown. The Name
thereof deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Abannage,</hi> a German Word ſignifying a
Portion.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>France</hi> has the Titl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Moſt Chriſtian King, and Elde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Son of the Church; the Eldeſt
Son o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the king is called
the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the preſumptive Heir of the Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Dutchies of <hi>Orleans, Anjou, Alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> and
<hi>Berry,</hi> as alſo the Earldom o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Evreux,</hi> have been the ordinary Titles of the other Sons
of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The number of the Peers of <hi>France,</hi> formerly conſiſted
but of Twelve, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The Archbiſhop and Duke of <hi>Rheims.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Biſhop and Duke of <hi>Lâon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Biſhop and Duke of <hi>Langres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Biſhop and Earl of <hi>Beauvais.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Biſhop and Earl of <hi>Noyon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Biſhop and Earl of <hi>Chaalons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Duke of <hi>Guyenne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Duke of <hi>Normandy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>Toulouſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>Champagne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Six Firſt were Eccleſiaſticks, and the reſt Laicks,
each with his particular <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29904:17"/>Function. The Inſtitution of
theſe Twelve peers, is attributed by ſome to <hi>Charlemain,</hi> by others
to <hi>Hugues-Capet;</hi> the Number of them is at preſent, no more in uſe,
except on the Coronation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; and that of the Laick Peers, is much greater than
it was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> is governed by an Abſolute King.<note place="margin">Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> The Crown is hereditary to his Family, and is
ſo far Particular, that the Legitimate Males alone can pretend to it, by the
Inſtitution of the Salick Law, which abſolutely excludes Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males; as we
have intimated before.</p>
            <p>One may reckon at preſent, Twelve Paliaments in the States of
<hi>France,</hi>ſince the Conqueſt of the French County. One may alſo
reckon Twenty Three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralties, or Offices of the Exchequer; Twenty Five
Mints, and Fourteen Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities: Whoſe Seats I ſhall obſerve in the
particular Diſcourſe of each City, where they are eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>It is pretended that the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> was
Inſtituted by <hi>Pepin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paris.</note> Father of
<hi>Charlemagne,</hi> and that it was ambula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, till <hi>Philip</hi> the
Fair, made it fixt in 1302. The Courts of Juſtice of the Iſle of
<hi>France, Champagne,</hi> the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Orleanois,</hi> and
all <hi>Lyonois</hi> 
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29904:18"/>are under its Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Toulouſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Toulouſe.</note>
was Inſtituted b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
ſame <hi>Philip</hi> the Fair, in the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Year, and was not fixed till under
<hi>Charle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the
Seventh, in 1443.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Rouen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rouen.</note> was
Inſtituted by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame
<hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh, in the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Year, and was fixed in 1503. unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the
Twelfth.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Grenoble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grenoble.</note> was
Inſtituted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentary, by the ſame <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, in the
Year 1453.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bourdeaux</note> was
Inſtituted by <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh, 1462.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Dijon</hi> was Inſtituted by the ſame King,<note place="margin">Dijon.</note> in 1476.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Aix,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aix.</note> by
<hi>Lewis</hi> the Twelfth, in the Year 1501.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Rennes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rennes.</note> was
Inſtituted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, in 1553.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Pau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pau.</note> by
<hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> in 1519.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Metz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Metz.</note> was
Inſtituted by the late King <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteeenth, in the Year
1633.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Tournay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tournay.</note> which
is called So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Council, was Inſtituted firxt by <hi>Lewis</hi> the
Fourteenth, the preſent King, in 1669.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Dole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dole.</note> was
Inſtituted in the <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29904:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Year— and rendred
ſedentary, by <hi>Philip</hi> the Good Duke of <hi>Bourgogne,</hi> in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Year 1422. It is at
preſent trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erred to
<hi>Beſanſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Parliaments have in their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſdiction, the Courts of Juſtice of thoſe
Cities, which are in the Government where they are eſtabliſhed. That of
<hi>Pau,</hi> extends it ſelf into <hi>Bearn,</hi> the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<hi>Navarre,</hi> and the Country of <hi>Labourd.</hi> And that of
<hi>Tournay</hi> to all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of <hi>France,</hi> in
<hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Hayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Roman Catholick Religion,<note place="margin">Religion.</note>
is exactly followed in <hi>France,</hi> yet the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed was Tolerated there
not long ſince, but with this Circumſtance, That all their Temples were
ſituated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Cities.</p>
            <p>There are computed in <hi>France</hi> Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
Arch-Biſhopricks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>18</hi> Arch-Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks,
<hi>106</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks.</note> ſince one may add thoſe of
<hi>Beſanſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and
106 Biſhopricks, which ſhall be obſerved in their due Places.</p>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29904:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CARDY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Province heretofore made par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the ancient <hi>Gaul Belgick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Name.</note> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is not an Author that could cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify to us, from whence this
Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Picardy</hi>
proceeds, which is notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding new.</p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf 132 Miles from <hi>Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Extent.</note> from between <hi>la Capelle</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rocroy;</hi> to the Mouth
of the River <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſle,</hi> which ſeparates it from <hi>Normand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and 102 from
<hi>South</hi> to <hi>North,</hi> fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Beauvaiſis</hi> to <hi>Calais.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> by
<hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> in the <hi>South</hi> by
the Iſle of <hi>France</hi> in the <hi>Weſt</hi> by the Britiſh Sea and
<hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy;</hi> and in the <hi>North</hi> by the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sea, and the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its Soil is very fertile in Corn,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> Paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Fruits; but it produces littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or no Wine.</p>
               <p>Its moſt conſiderable Rivers are the <hi>Oiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> which receives the <hi>Serre,</hi> the <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
Authie</hi> and <hi>Canche.</hi> The two firſt are towards the
<hi>Eaſt,</hi> and the other three run to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> where they
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29904:19"/>themſelves into the Sea.</p>
               <p>In this Government are comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Picardy</hi> and <hi>Artois,</hi> to which
one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay at preſent add the
Conqueſts of the King in <hi>Flanders, Haynault,</hi> Dutchy of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uxembourg</hi> and <hi>Cambreſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Picardy</hi> is divided into Seven little Provinces,<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> which keep the following Order in their
Situation. Firſt <hi>la Tie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ache</hi> lyes about the Rivers <hi>Oiſe</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erre; le Vermandois, Santerre,
l' Amie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ois,</hi> which is
<hi>Picardy</hi> properly ſpeaking,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>Ponthieu</hi> may be
obſerved follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the courſe of the River <hi>Somme.</hi> Then <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Boulonis,</hi> to which is
added the <hi>Pais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>econquis,</hi> with the Principality of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres,</hi> which is
more advanced towards the <hi>North,</hi> between the Sea and
<hi>Artois.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Amiens.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AMiens</hi> upon the <hi>Somme,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Capital.</note> is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of all the Province. 'Tis a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ery ancient, fair, and well
fortified City. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t is alſo
honoured with an Epiſcopal See under the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Rheims,</hi> a
Mint, a Generality, and a Preſidial; ſubject to the French King. It
ſtands in the Road from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Calais,</hi> about 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29904:20"/>70 Miles from each. Lon. 21.26. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 49, 44.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Abbeville.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abbeville</hi> is a Modern City, divide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the River <hi>Somme,</hi>
Capital <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the County of
<hi>Ponthieu,</hi> which deriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> its Name from the great number
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Bridges, which are to be
ſeen full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Water, Lakes and
Marſhes; which d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> charge
themſelves into the Sea, near S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Valery,</hi> which is a very ancient Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. About 84.
Miles from <hi>Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
Lon. 21.00. Lat. 50.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Boulogne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BOulogne</hi> is a fair and large City, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vided in two parts, the one is
cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper
City,</hi> and the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Lower;</hi> becauſe 'tis built in a Plain ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> joyning to the Sea, where there is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Haven. The
<hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper</hi> is well Fortified and has a conſiderable Caſtle. The
en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> trance of the port is a
little dangerou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and there
is more difficulty in bringing Ships in ſecure, than in that of
<hi>Calais<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29904:20"/>The River <hi>Liane</hi> waſhes its Walls, and then goes
to diſcharge it ſelf into the Sea near <hi>Dunefort.</hi> It is a
Biſhoprick under the <hi>A.</hi> of <hi>Rheims,</hi> about 17 Miles from
<hi>Calais,</hi> 40 from <hi>Abbeville,</hi> and 125 from <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon.
20.46. Lat. 50.47.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Calais.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAlais</hi> in the County of <hi>Oye,</hi> is a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo
important to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> that it is as it were, the Key of
<hi>France</hi> on the Sea-ſide. Its Situation is in a curious Plain, and the
Ditches filled with the Sea. The Port is very commodious and ſecure, by
reaſon of two Towers that defend it from all Oppoſers, It ſtands on the
Sea, about 19 Mile off <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> 96 off <hi>London,</hi> and 140 off
<hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 21.4. Lat. 51.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Arras.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ARras</hi> upon the <hi>Searpe,</hi> is the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of
the Country of <hi>Artois.</hi> It is a large, fair and ſtrong City; an
Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal See under the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray,</hi> 
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29904:21"/>ſubject to the French King.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 15 Miles off
<hi>Doway,</hi> 20 off <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray,</hi> 92 off <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 21.55. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 50.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Saint-Omer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SAint-Omer</hi> a Biſhops See upon
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Aa,</hi> and
<hi>Aire</hi> upon the <hi>Velule,</hi> bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>Artois,</hi> were yielded to the King
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Spain</hi> by the Peace
of 1659. But find the French are become Maſters of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> Lon. 21.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lat. 50.52.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Tournay.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TOurnay</hi> upon the <hi>Scheld,</hi> is an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal
City of <hi>Flanders,</hi> which <hi>Lew is</hi> the Fourteenth, has honoured
with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sovereign Council;
under whoſe Juri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
are all the Courts of Juſtice i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> depending upon <hi>France.</hi> About 20 Miles off
<hi>Doway,</hi> and 32 off <hi>Mons.</hi> Lon. 22.36. Lat. 50.43<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29904:21"/>
                  <head>Cambray.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAmbray</hi> upon the <hi>Scheld,</hi> is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of
<hi>Cambreſis,</hi> an Arch-Biſhops See, Fortiſied with one of the beſt
Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadels of all the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> which has a long time ſerved as
a Bulwork a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spaniards. Within 34 Miles of <hi>Mons,</hi> 40 off
<hi>Amiens,</hi> and 94 off <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Luxmbourgh</hi> Capital of its
Province, and <hi>Valencienne</hi> upon the <hi>Scheld,</hi> are alſo very
conſiderable Places. Lon. 22.24. Lat. 50.51.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ypres</hi> is a ſtrong City of the
<hi>Low-Countries,</hi> in the Earldom of <hi>Flanders,</hi> a Biſhoprick
under the <hi>A.</hi> of <hi>Mech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n;</hi> ſubject to the French. It ſtands in a fruitful Plain,
within 18 Miles off <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> 23 off <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and 35 off
<hi>Ghent.</hi> Lon. 22.3. Lat. 50.57.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dunkirk</hi> is a ſtrong Sea-Port Town and Caſtle in
the Earldom of <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſubject to the French; about to Miles from
<hi>Graveling,</hi> 16 off <hi>Newport,</hi> 19 off <hi>Calais,</hi> and 24 off
<hi>Oſtend.</hi> Lon. 21.30. Lat. 51.7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mons</hi> or <hi>Bergen,</hi> a very ſtrong and rich
City of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> Capital <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29904:22"/>of
<hi>Haiuault,</hi> ſubject to the French, and taken in 1691, about 27 Miles
from <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> 37 from <hi>Namur,</hi> 120 from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi>
Lon. 23.12. Lat. 50.28.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>NOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANDY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Province has loſt much of its antient Luſtre,<note place="margin">Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages.</note> and the Authority which it had in the time of
its antient Dukes, who were Sovereign Princes ſo Powerful, that they have
often ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long and impetuous Wars againſt the Kings of <hi>France,
England</hi> and other Princes, with whom they have many times contracted
Alliances.</p>
               <p>It was formerly called the Weſtern <hi>Neuſtrie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Name.</note> and the name of <hi>Normandy</hi> was given to it
upon the account of the Northern People who came to inhabit there; for
<hi>Nord-man</hi> in High-Dutch, ſignifies Man of the North.</p>
               <p>It is Situated upon the Channel,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> and may extend about 186 Miles from Eaſt to
Weſt, from <hi>Aumale</hi> to the Weſtern ſide of <hi>Coutantin;</hi> and
129 from South to North-eaſt, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Alenſon,</hi> to the
City of <hi>Eu.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29904:22"/>
               <p>The Britiſh Sea, or the Channel,<note place="margin">Bounds.</note> bounds it in the North and Weſt; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the
Eaſt, it has the Iſle of <hi>France,</hi> and the Country of
<hi>Perche,</hi> with that of <hi>Maine</hi> towards the South.</p>
               <p>The Soil is Fertile enough in Corn,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> Paſturage and Hemp, and abounds in Wood and
Fruits; it produces but little or no Wine, Cyder and Beer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt
uſual Liquors. There is to be found alſo ſeveral Mines of Iron. Fiſh is
ſo common there, that it is as it were given away. There are very good
Quarries for Structure, and alſo your Marble, Slat, &amp;c. not ſlightly to
be eſteemed of. As for Mineral Waters, they are to be met with in divers
Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; thoſe of Forges are of the greateſt Repute, and moſt frequented.
The Country excels in many agreeable Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, in number of Fir-Trees, and a
great quantity of White Salt, which is conveyed to <hi>Paris.</hi> The
Inhabitants 'tis ſaid are ſo diſpoſed to plead one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another,
and ſo well verſed in all the Tricks of the Court, that they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem much
rather to go to the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Juſtice, than to reconcile mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by
Civility and Sweetneſs, and without having recourſe to Proceſs, 
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29904:23"/>which is the reaſon that the very Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks are
almoſt all Lawyers. I have read a Story of Two Neighbours, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quarrell'd to that Extremity
about a Mag-Py's Neſt which was built upon one Man's Tree, and inclined over
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Land of the other, that
they redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced themſelves to the very brink o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ruin.</p>
               <p>Its chief Rivers are the <hi>Seine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which the <hi>Eure</hi> diſcharges it ſelf and the
<hi>Rille,</hi> which hides it ſelf under ground for the ſpace of a League
nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aumont le Roger;</hi> the
<hi>Orne</hi> which goes up to <hi>Caen,</hi> and the <hi>Vere</hi> which
paſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by St.
<hi>Lo,</hi> and ſeparates the Biſhoprich of <hi>Coutance</hi> from that of
<hi>Bayeux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Government extends it ſelf no further than this
Province,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> which is divided into Upper and
Lower: The Upper comprehends the Bayliwicks of <hi>Roüen, Evreux,
Caux,</hi> and <hi>Giſors:</hi> The Lower thoſe of <hi>Caën
Alenſon,</hi> and <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> It is again divided into Seven
Dioceſſes, whoſe Epiſcopal Cities are <hi>Roüen, Liſieux,
Bayeux, Coutance, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranche, Seez,</hi> and <hi>Evreux.</hi> The Four Firſt
are to be found in order upon the Channel of <hi>England,</hi> going from
Eaſt to Weſt; the Three others are to the <pb n="35" facs="tcp:29904:23"/>South of
them, and meet in their turn from Weſt to Eaſt.</p>
               <p>The Dioceſs of <hi>Roüen</hi> comprehends Four little
Countries, which are called <hi>Caux, Bray, Vexin, Normand,</hi> and
<hi>Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais:</hi> In that of <hi>Caux,</hi> there is the Land of
<hi>Yvelot,</hi> which certain Authors Miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, have pretended to have
been raiſed to a Kingdom by King <hi>Clotaire:</hi> But this Opinion is of no
credit, and it only bears the Title of a Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>To the Weſt of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Coutance,</hi> one
finds the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> under the 18 Deg. 10 Min. of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude,
and the 49.30 Min. of Latitude; and the Iſle of <hi>Garnſey,</hi> under the
17.40 Min. of Longitude, and the 49.30 Min. of Latitude, and ſeveral other
little Adjacent Iſles.</p>
               <p>Theſe Iſlands are in the Authority of the King of
<hi>England,</hi> and theſe Two may have each about 24 or 30 Miles of
Circuit, and were heretofore a part of <hi>Normandy.</hi> The moſt
conſiderable Cities take as follows.</p>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:29904:24"/>
                  <head>Rouen.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ROüen</hi> or <hi>Roan,</hi> upon the River
<hi>Seine,</hi> is the Capital of <hi>Normandy,</hi> a very large and ſtately
City, one of the beſt of <hi>France,</hi> and moſt advantagiouſly Seated
for Trade, by reaſon of the Flux and Reflux of the Sea; it has an
Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, a Parliament, and a Sea-Port, which are Three things that will
at any time make a City recommendable; and alſo a Mint and a Generality. Its
Situation is in a delightful Plain, bordered on one ſide with ſeveral
agreeable Mountains covered with Trees, and on the other ſide, waſh'd with
the River <hi>Seine;</hi> to which are adjoyning many pleaſant Meadows. The
Cathedral Church is a very ſtately Building, in which there are Three Towers,
whereof one is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Lead, which Time ſeems to have changed almoſt
into the colour of Copper, and whoſe Height is above 550 Steps: The Tombs of
the Dukes of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and the Arch-biſhops of the Place; the Statue
of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth in White Marble; its Organs of an extraordinary
bigneſs, the Body of <pb n="37" facs="tcp:29904:24"/>it ſupported by Twenty One
Pillars, but more particularly the Choir and Sacerdotal Ornaments, preſented
by <hi>William</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal
<hi>Amboiſe,</hi> as alſo its Treaſure, which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s very curious to ſee,
upon the account of the Splendour and Riches of the Veſſels, Mitres,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> all emboſs'd with Gold and Stones of Value; but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
a Sacred Mantle of Needle-Work, repreſenting Jeſus Chriſt amongſt the
Doctors, in the middle, receiving Baptiſm by St. <hi>John,</hi> all which is
very glorious and remarkable; beſides many other Curioſities, which it
would be too tedious to inſert. There is one thing very obſervable upon the
portal of this Church, which is a Triumphant Arch, repreſenting
<hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, who chaſes the Lions and the Wolves from his
Flock, and encourageth his Sheep; whilſt on the other ſide he ſees the
Ligue bound in chains, and King of <hi>Spain</hi> who is near a Clock,
penſive and Melancholy at the ſight of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny illuſtrious Actions.
The Government of the Province makes his uſual reſidence at
<hi>Roüen,</hi> which is within 60 Miles of <hi>Amiens,</hi> 69 of
<hi>Paris,</hi> and 145 of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Lon. 20.2. Lat. 49.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:29904:25"/>
                  <head>Caen.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAën</hi> upon the River <hi>Orne,</hi> paſſes
fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Second City of
<hi>Normandy,</hi> both as to its Extent, Antiquity. and Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis
ſaid that this City became ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rich and Powerful by the reſidence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Engliſh during their Wars
with <hi>France,</hi> and alſo by reaſon of the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Privileges it is inveſted with: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
the Univerſity, founded by <hi>Charle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> the Seventh, it is honoured with a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality, a Preſidial
and a Bayliwick Moreover it is enriched with Nineteen or Twenty Churches,
beſides a great number of Religious Houſes; about 70 Miles from
<hi>Roüen</hi> Lon. 18.12. Lat. 49.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Diepe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DIepe</hi> is a Town of Reputation, by reaſon of its
noble Haven, and the great quantity of good Merchandiſe and the vaſt
Traffick it makes in all Places of <hi>Europe.</hi> The River <hi>Argue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> on which it ſtands,
renders it exceeding <pb n="39" facs="tcp:29904:25"/>pleaſant; and the Inhabitants have
the glory of making the beſt Compaſſes, and moſt exact Quadrants of the
World, as alſo all other Inſtruments neceſſary to Aſtrology, as well
as the Sea. It is about 35 Miles from <hi>Roüen,</hi> and 62 from
<hi>Haſtings</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> Lon. 20.4. Lat. 49.59.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Havre de Grace.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAvre de Grace,</hi> is a Fortreſs built by
<hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, to oppoſe the Engliſh, and to make a Haven
of, to ſerve as a Retreat for the Merchants of the Nation, and a Magazine of
Ships of War. 'Tis ſaid, that it is capable of holding 2000 Sail and more; if
ſo, it muſt be one of the moſt conſiderable Ports in <hi>Europe.</hi>
It has a ſtrong Caſtle, and ſtands nigh the Mouth of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>Seine,</hi> about 48 Miles from <hi>Roüen.</hi> Lon. 28.44. Lat.
44.42.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Bayeux.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BAieux</hi> (the <hi>Civitas Baiocaſſium</hi> of
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus</hi>) remarkable of a long time <pb n="40" facs="tcp:29904:26"/>for a
Biſhops See. One of the Biſhops whereof called <hi>Odo,</hi> Brother to
<hi>William</hi> the Conqueror by the Mothers ſide, was by him created Earl
of <hi>Kent,</hi> and afterwards upon ſome diſpleaſure made Priſoner;
for which, when reprimand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Pope, (the Clergy being then exempted from
the Secular Authority,) he returned this Anſwer, that he had committed the
Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> not the Biſhop of <hi>Baieux;</hi> by which
diſtinction he avoided the Pope's Diſpleaſure. It ſtands nigh the Sea,
about 16 Miles off <hi>Caen,</hi> 45 off <hi>Coutances,</hi> and 84 off
<hi>Roüen.</hi> Lon. 17.49. Lat. 49.28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Coutances.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COutances</hi> and <hi>Auranches</hi> are both me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable
upon the account of their Epiſcopal Sees; from the former, the Country
thereabouts hath the Name of <hi>Coutantin.</hi> The latter is Situate upon a
Rock, with a fair proſpect over the Engliſh Channel, within 28 Miles of
each other. The Lon. of the former is 16.45. the Lat. 49.9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29904:26"/>
                  <head>Evreux.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EVreux</hi> and <hi>Liſieux,</hi> are Biſhops Sees,
the former being the Mediolanium of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and ſtill a rich and
flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Town, being the Third in eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all this Province. The
Firſt is about 27 Miles from <hi>Roüen,</hi> and 58 from <hi>Paris.</hi>
The laſt about 45 from <hi>Roüen</hi> and <hi>Evreux. Seez</hi> alſo
is an Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal See, and ſtands on the Fountains of the River
<hi>Orne,</hi> about 13 Miles from <hi>Alenſon,</hi> 33 off
<hi>Liſieux,</hi> and 64 off <hi>Roüen.</hi> The Lon. of the former is
20.4. Lat. 49.2.</p>
                  <p>What the Revenues of this Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom might amount to in former
times, is not eaſie to affirm. That they were very fair and large, appears by
the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Philip de Comines,</hi> who ſays that he had ſeen
raiſed in <hi>Normandy</hi> 95000 l. Sterling, which was a Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Sum of
Mony in thoſe times. Now they amount to as much as the King's Toll-Maſters
are pleaſed to exact.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29904:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of the Iſle of <hi>FRANCE</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF this Government is the leaſt exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the Twelve, which we ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved in the Diviſion
of <hi>France, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it
is without contradiction the moſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vantagious and charming, not only u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on the account of its natural Beau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the ſtately Houſes of
Pleaſure whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are to be
met with therein, but alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
the advantage of enjoying for the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> part the Preſence of the King a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Court.</p>
               <p>The Iſle of <hi>France,</hi> to ſpeak wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> propriety, is compriſed
between the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vers of
<hi>Seine, Marne, Oiſe</hi> and <hi>Aiſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> but there is added to in ſome parts
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the adjoyning Provinces
whereof i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Government is
compoſed to accompan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
ſomewhat better the Metropolis of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdom. It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
the Iſle of <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to diſtinguiſh it from the main Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and is made to exten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> from Eaſt to Weſt,
<hi>viz.</hi> fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon the <hi>Aiſne</hi> to
<hi>Giſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and as
many from North to South from beyond <hi>Noyon</hi> to <hi>Courteny</hi> in
<hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinois.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29904:27"/>
               <p>It is bounded on the North with <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> on the Eaſt with <hi>Champagne</hi> and <hi>la
Brie,</hi> on the South with <hi>Gaſtinois</hi> and <hi>la Beauſſe,</hi>
and on the Weſt with <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soil is very Fruitful in excellent Corn,<note place="margin">Soil.</note> and produces a ſufficient quantity of Wine and
Fruits: A Country gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally very Delectable, and ſo Fertile withal, that the
Hills are equal to the Vallies in moſt Places of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongſt the Rivers are remarked the <hi>Seine,</hi> which
receives the <hi>Marne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> and the
<hi>Oiſe,</hi> which is encreaſed by the Waters of the <hi>Aiſne,</hi>
which runs by <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> and the <hi>Terrain,</hi> which waſhes
the Walls of <hi>Beauvais.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was formerly part of the Province of <hi>Belgica
Secunda,</hi> and <hi>Lugdunenſis quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> and is now divided into Four parts, namely, 1.
The Dukedom of <hi>Valois;</hi> 2. <hi>Gaſtinois;</hi> 3. <hi>Heurepois;</hi>
and 4. That which is properly called the Iſle of <hi>France,</hi> by ſome
the County of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Paris.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PAris</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>France,</hi> properly ſo
called, is the Metropolis not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this Government, but of the whole 
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29904:28"/>Kingdom: It is in Compaſs about Eigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Miles, of an Orbicular Form, agreeabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeated on the Diviſions of
the <hi>Seine,</hi> a Fair, Large and Populous City, but fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhort of the Oſtentations
of the French one of whoſe Authors coming to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>London,</hi>
ſays, that it is (with as Emphaſis.) as large as <hi>Paris,</hi> the
Subur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> comprehended. Whereas
if the trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were
impartially delivered, <hi>Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> would be found to exceed the other.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was thought in
<hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh time time, to contain 500000 People
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all ſorts of Ages, which
muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably encreaſed ſince that King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> time. The Fortifications are of n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> good aſſurance, inſomuch
that when once a Pariſian bragg'd that their Town was never taken by Force,
an Engliſh-Man replied, that the reaſon of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was, becauſe on the leaſt Calamity i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> uſed to Capitulate. It has
the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of Boats and Barges ſerved by the River <hi>Seine,</hi> as
the <hi>Thame</hi> Weſtward doth <hi>London.</hi> It has an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Arch-Biſhop and an
Univerſity of great repute, conſiſting of 52 Colledges, whereof 40 are of
little uſe. It is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Parliament City, and the uſual Seat of the French King, when abſent from 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29904:28"/>
                     <hi>Verſailles.</hi> It is about 170 Miles from
<hi>Antwerp,</hi> 208 from <hi>London,</hi> 250 from <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 600
from <hi>Vienna.</hi> Lon. 21.30. Lat. 48.45.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Soiſſons.</head>
                  <p>THE City of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> is very ancient, and was
heretofore of great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute: It is ſeated upon the River <hi>Aiſne,</hi> in
a very agreeable Plain, encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with Fruiful Mountains.
<hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomy</hi> calls it <hi>Auguſta Sueſſonum;</hi> and before him,
<hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Commentaries ſpeaks of <hi>Galba,</hi> one of its
Kings, and ſays, that in his time it was very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, commanded Twelve
Cities, and could ſet our an Army of 50000 Men.</p>
                  <p>It is eaſie to judge that it was the moſt conſiderable
of <hi>Gaul Belgick,</hi> ſince the Praetors made it their reſiding Place.
It is a Biſhops See, a Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a Bayliwick, a Preſidial,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> about 28 Miles from <hi>Rheims,</hi> 33 off St.
<hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> and 48 off <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 22.32. Lat. 49.19.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:29904:29"/>
                  <head>Laon.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LAon</hi> is an Epiſcopal City, the Biſhop whereof is
one of the Twelve Peers of <hi>France,</hi> and Earl of <hi>Laon,</hi> in Latin
<hi>Laodunum;</hi> ſituated upon a Mountain of difficult acceſs, about 24
Miles from <hi>Rheims,</hi> 15 from <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> and 66 from
<hi>Paris,</hi> Long. 22.48. Lat. 49.30. <hi>Noyon</hi> near the River
<hi>Oyſe, Beauvais</hi> upon the <hi>Terrain,</hi> and <hi>Senlis</hi> on the
River <hi>Nonette</hi> are alſo Biſhops Sees.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>CHAMPAGNE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Country was heretofore famous through the Grandeure of its
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Earls, who were Sovereign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and withal ſo powerful, that
they have ſuſtained long and vigorous Wars againſt the Kings of
<hi>France</hi> and <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> and ſo nobly eſteemed of, that
thoſe Kings have not diſdained to ſeek their Alliance. They bear the
Title of Earl and Pear of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:29904:29"/>
               <p>Its Name undoubtedly proceeds from the delightful and ſpacious
Plains that are therein, particularly about <hi>Rheims</hi> and
<hi>Chaalons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf above 138 Miles from Weſt to
South-Eaſt, from <hi>Lagny</hi> in <hi>Brie</hi> to
<hi>Bourbonnecls-Bains</hi> in <hi>Baſſigny:</hi> and 162 from South to
North, from <hi>Ravieres</hi> in <hi>Senonois</hi> to <hi>Rocroy</hi> in
<hi>Rhetelo.</hi> It is bounded on the North by the Duchy of <hi>Luxemburg</hi>
and <hi>Haynault:</hi> on the Eaſt by <hi>Lorrain:</hi> on the South by
<hi>Burgundy:</hi> and on the Weſt by the Iſle of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soil is for the moſt part white and chalky, bearing no
other Corn but Rye: yet it produces moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Wine. There are but few
Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts towards the South; but in the Nothern part they are more frequent,
where alſo is to be found ſeveral Mines of Iron.</p>
               <p>Its principal Rivers are the <hi>Seine,</hi> which receives the
<hi>Ionne</hi> and the <hi>Aube;</hi> the <hi>Marne;</hi> the <hi>Aiſne;</hi>
and the <hi>Veſle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Government comprehends <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne</hi> and <hi>Brie.
Champagne</hi> is divided into Upper and Lower. The firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes the
Territories of <hi>Chaalons</hi> and <hi>Rheims, Perſhois, Rethelois</hi> and
the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality <pb n="48" facs="tcp:29904:30"/>of <hi>Sedan</hi> and <hi>Raucort</hi>
with the Provoſtſhip of <hi>Donchery.</hi> The other comprehends the
Territory of <hi>Troyes Vallage</hi> and <hi>Baſſigny,</hi> together with
<hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonois.</hi> The chief Cities are</p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Troyes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TRoyes</hi> upon the <hi>Seine,</hi> is the
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital</hi> City of the whole Province. It was the Habitation of the
ancient Earls of <hi>Champagne, whoſe Tombs it</hi> ſtill preſerves; it
doth now encloſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Juriſdictions, being one of the beſt of the
Kingdom, very populous and rich, upon the account of its Fairs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by a
great number of ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Merchants. Among other things they make here a
vaſt Quantity of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. It is adorned with an Epiſcopal See, a Mint and a
Preſidial. About 32 Miles from <hi>Sens,</hi> 68 from <hi>Rheims,</hi> and 80
from <hi>Paris,</hi> Longitude 23.17. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude 48.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:29904:30"/>
                  <head>Rheims.</head>
                  <p>AN Archbiſhops See, who is the firſt Duke and Peer of
<hi>France,</hi> ſeated upon the River <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſle.</hi> At this City the
Kings of <hi>France</hi> are uſually crowned, that ſo they may enjoy the
Unction of a ſacred Oil preſerved in the Cathedral Church here, which they
ſay, came down from Heaven, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver decreaſeth, the Truth of which I
leave to the Reader's Judgment, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, eſpecially if he has read
<hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory d' Tours,</hi> who is ſo prodigal of his Miracles, and yet doth
not mention this. The Arch-Biſhop hereof has the Glory and Privilege of
anointing the French Kings. It is a Preſidial See, and an Univerſity of no
ſmall eſteem, wherein there is a College appointed for the Education of
young Engliſh Fugitives. The firſt Seminary for this purpoſe was erected
at <hi>Doway,</hi> in the year 1568. A ſecond at <hi>Rome</hi> by Pope
<hi>Gregory</hi> the Thirteenth; a 3d. at <hi>Valladolid</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi>
by King <hi>Philip</hi> II. a fourth in <hi>Lovain,</hi> a Town of
<hi>Brabant;</hi> and a fifth here by the Dukes of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> about 72
miles <pb n="50" facs="tcp:29904:31"/>from <hi>Paris,</hi> Longitude 23.18. Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
49.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Sens.</head>
                  <p>BEtween the Rivers <hi>Yonne</hi> and <hi>Seine</hi> ſtands
the City of <hi>Sens, (Civita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Senonum</hi> in <hi>Antoninus)</hi> renowned for the ancient
Senonois, who made great Conqueſts in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Greece.</hi> The
Cathedral Church has Ornaments of an immenſe value, the Appurtenances of the
Altar being of Maſſy Gold, garniſhed with Pearls. It has an Archbiſhop,
who ſtyles himſelf Primate of the Gauls; alſo a Bayliwick and a
Preſidial. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 30 Miles from <hi>Troyes,</hi> 28 from <hi>Auxerre,</hi> 60
from <hi>Paris,</hi> Long. 22.29. Lat. 48.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Langres.</head>
                  <p>THe Capital of <hi>Baſſigny</hi> ſeated very
advantagiouſly near the River <hi>Marne,</hi> and not far from the
Head-Spring or Fountain of the River <hi>Seine.</hi> One may ſee here Marks
of a great Antiquity; 'tis very ſtrong, and has the <pb n="51" facs="tcp:29904:31"/>Reputation of being never taken. Its Biſhop is a Duke and one of the
twelve ancient Peers of <hi>France;</hi> He is alſo a Marquis, Earl and
Baron: It has alſo a Preſidial See. About 40 Miles from <hi>Dijon,</hi> 56
from <hi>Troyes,</hi> Long. 24.32. Lat. 47.44.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Chaalons,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Marne</hi> is famous for the great quantity
of Woollen-Cloth it conveys to <hi>Paris</hi> by way of the <hi>Marne.</hi> In
the year 453. there was a memorable Battel fought in the Neighbouring Plains,
where <hi>Attila</hi> King of the Huns, who qualified him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Scourge of
God, was defeated by <hi>Merouee,</hi> aſſiſted by <hi>Theodoric</hi>
King of the Viſigoths, who was ſlain, and <hi>Aetius</hi> Lieutenant to the
Emperor <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian</hi> the Third; 180000 Men were left upon the place.
It is a Biſhops See, who is an Earl and Peer, and has a Generality and
Preſidial. About 24 Miles from <hi>Rheims,</hi> 50 from <hi>Troyes,</hi>
Long. 23.38. Lat. 48.54.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:29904:32"/>
                  <head>Rethel.</head>
                  <p>BEtween the <hi>Aiſne</hi> and the <hi>Meuſe</hi> lies
<hi>Rethel,</hi> which communicates its Name to the Dutchy of
<hi>Rethelois,</hi> and which is at preſent called <hi>Mazarin.</hi> Few
Cities have been ſo often taken, as this has been in the laſt Wars. There
was an expectation in theſe Quarters of Seeing the Conjunction of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>Aiſne</hi> with the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> by the means of the little River
<hi>Barre,</hi> and ſo to have the conveniences of Navigation by Rivers from
<hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Holland;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 22 Miles from <hi>Rheims,</hi> and
24 from <hi>Chaalons,</hi> Long. 23.42. Lat. 49.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Brie.</head>
                  <p>THis Province is ſituated between the <hi>Seine</hi> and the
<hi>Marne,</hi> and its Extent from Eaſt to Weſt is about 30 or 36 Miles,
from North to South much the ſame diſtance.</p>
                  <p>Its Soil is not every where alike; for near <hi>Champagne</hi>
and towards <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teau-Thierry</hi> 
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:29904:32"/>it produces tolerable
Wine; and towards the Iſle of <hi>France,</hi> as alſo about
<hi>Meaux,</hi> the Wine is much groſſer. There is every where good ſtore
of Corn, delicious Fruits, and good Paſturage. The Country is very fine, and
very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable for the diverſion of Hunting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Meaux.</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Marne</hi> is the moſt conſiderable of
the Cities of the Upper <hi>Brie.</hi> It is very ancient, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with a
Biſhoprick and a Bayli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick; about 24 Miles from <hi>Paris.
Chateau-Thierry</hi> upon the ſame River bears the Title of Dutchy, and
paſſes for the Capital of the Upper <hi>Brie.</hi> It is adorned with a
Bayliwick, and a Preſidial See. <hi>Provins</hi> upon the little River of
<hi>Vouzie,</hi> is received by ſome for the Metropolis of all <hi>Brie,</hi>
ſeated in the Lower, and is ſufficiently known for the excellent Conſerve
of Roſes, which is made there.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:29904:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>BRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAGNE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter that <hi>Maximus</hi> had uſurped the Empire, and that
the Army which he commanded in <hi>England,</hi> had proclaimed him Emperour,
<hi>Conan,</hi> one of his moſt famous Captains, who had been very
aſſiſtant to him in that great undertaking, ſoon obtained a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
for his Services. The Emperor gave him the poſſeſſion of
<hi>Bretagne,</hi> whereof <hi>Conan</hi> took the Quality of King, in the year
300. His Succeſſors quitted this noble Title in 878. under the Reign of
<hi>Lewis le Begue</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> to take the Quality of Earls.
At length they were made Dukes and Peers in 1520. and became very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful by
their great Alliances. The laſt of its Dukes dying, left only a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
who was married to <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth, and afterwards to
<hi>Lewis</hi> the Twelfth, Kings of <hi>France.</hi> Thus this Dukedom was
united to the Crown, from which it has not been diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſince.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29904:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bretagne</hi> was anciently called <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Name.</note> as being ſituated along the Sea. Some pretend that
its new Name was given to it by ſome People of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> who
came to inhabit there, or elſe from <hi>Brutus</hi> King of the Gauls; but
there is more probability, that this Name proceeds from an old Gauliſh word
called <hi>Brit,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>painted,</hi> becauſe its ancient
Inhabitants uſed to paint their Beards and their Hair.</p>
               <p>This Province has about 180 Miles from Eaſt to Weſt,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> from beyond <hi>Vitrey</hi> to the Point of
<hi>Conquet;</hi> and 120 from South to North, from the Iſle of
<hi>Boüin</hi> to the Mouth of the River <hi>Coüonon,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
St. <hi>Michael's</hi> Mount.</p>
               <p>It is bounded on the Eaſt by <hi>Anjou</hi> and
<hi>Main,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> advancing it ſelf towards the
Weſt like a Peninſula, to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, which confines it on the other
ſides.</p>
               <p>The Soil abounds in excellent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturage and Cattel,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> from whence they furniſh themſelves with very
good But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: They have good ſtore of Corn, ſome Wine, Linnen, and Fruits
in a great quantity. They make Salt upon the Coaſts, and abound in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
Fiſh. Here alſo are the beſt Sea-Ports of the whole Kingdom.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:29904:34"/>
               <p>Amongſt the Number of Rivers which water this Country,<note place="margin">Rivers.</note> is obſerved the <hi>Loire;</hi> the
<hi>Villaine,</hi> which receives the <hi>Ouſte:</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Blavet,
Auffen, Trieux,</hi> and <hi>Rance.</hi> Yet theſe laft are no where
conſiderable, but at their Mouths.</p>
               <p>The Government of <hi>Bretagne</hi> is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited in this ſingle
Province,<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> which is divided into Upper and
Lower, this towards the Weſt, and the other to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt. They that
conſider the different Languages of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, divide it into three
parts; they attribute to the Biſhopricks of <hi>Dol Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> and St.
<hi>Malo</hi> the uſe of the French Tongue; they ſay that the Britiſh
Tongue, which is a remainder of the Gauliſh, is received amongſt the
Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Biſhopricks of <hi>Cornoüaille,</hi> St. <hi>Pol de
Leon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>Trequier:</hi> They give a mixt Language to the
Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks of <hi>Nantes, Vennes,</hi> and St. <hi>Brieux.</hi> Theſe
Nine Biſhopricks are under the Archbiſhop of <hi>Tours.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29904:34"/>
                  <head>Rennes.</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Villaine</hi> is the largeſt City,<note place="margin">Capital.</note> and Capital of the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, the uſual
Reſidence of a Biſhop, and Parliament. It is ſeated in the Upper
<hi>Bretagne,</hi> and has the Privilege of coining Mony; about 50 Miles from
<hi>Nantes.</hi> 115 from <hi>Rochelle,</hi> &amp;c. Long. 16.30. Lat.
48.3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Nantes,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Loire,</hi> is the ſtrongeſt, and more
commodious for Traffick by the means of the <hi>Loire,</hi> over which it has a
very fine Bridge, and by reaſon of the Flux and Reflux of the Sea. Under the
Name of <hi>Cardivicum,</hi> and <hi>Corbilo</hi> it is eſteemed one of the
three moſt ancient Cities of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> has a Generality, a Mint,
and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. It was the Habitation
of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dukes of
<hi>Bretagne</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of
their Eldeſt Sons, under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
of Earls, as alſo <hi>Dinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of their
Youngeſt, It is a Biſhops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:29904:35"/>as St. <hi>Malo, Dol,</hi> and St.
<hi>Brieux;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 44 Miles from <hi>Angers,</hi> 68 from
<hi>Rochelle,</hi> Long. 16.48. Lat. 47.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>St. Malo.</head>
                  <p>THe ſtrong Situation of St. <hi>Malo</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sea, and
its vaſt Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Foreign Countries render it one of the moſt
conſiderable places of the Kingdom. It is guarded at Night by very fierce
Dogs of an Engliſh Breed, which go the Rounds of the City. The Diſcovery of
<hi>Canada</hi> is owing to one of its Inhabitants, called <hi>James
Cartier.</hi> In the year 1661. it ſuffered a great Loſs by a Fire, which
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed a part of the Houſes; about 12 Miles from <hi>Dol,</hi> and 42
from <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> Long. 16.8. Lat. 48.40.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Dol.</head>
                  <p>IT ſtands in a Marſhy Ground, and is ſaid to contain
ſome Family, who bear the Name of <hi>Devils,</hi> perhaps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they
are the Remainders of the ancient People <hi>Diablintes,</hi> Some Dukes 
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29904:35"/>of <hi>Bretagne</hi> had a deſign to have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the
Biſhoprick of <hi>Dol</hi> into an Archbiſhoprick. About 33 Miles from
<hi>Rennes,</hi> Long. 16.22. Lat. 48.34. St. <hi>Brieux</hi> a Biſhops See,
was the only City, which preſerved it ſelf during the Wars between the
Families of <hi>Blois</hi> and <hi>Mont fort;</hi> it ſtands on the Sea
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 55 Miles from <hi>Rennes.</hi> The Five foregoing Cities are in the
Upper <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Breſt.</head>
                  <p>IN a Gulf, where the Sea makes Four different Entries, is
eſteemed one of the beſt Sea-Ports of <hi>Europe:</hi> Indeed the Ships are
always afloat there, were they of Two Thouſand Tun. It is the principal
Magazine of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty of <hi>France</hi> for Veſſels, which go upon
the Ocean; ſeated in the Lower <hi>Bretagne.</hi> About 125 Miles from,
<hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> 120 from St. <hi>Malo,</hi> 320 from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> Long.
13.18. Lat. 47.58.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:29904:36"/>
                  <head>Blavet.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BLavet,</hi> aliás <hi>Port-Loüis,</hi> was
former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to the Spaniards by thoſe of the <hi>Ligue:</hi> and during
the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe of the Reformed Religion, the Sieur <hi>de
Soubiſe</hi> had a deſign to render himſelf Maſter of it. This and
<hi>Breſt</hi> bear the Lawrel from all the reſt by reaſon of their
ſtrong Fortifications together with the Goodneſs and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their
Ports. It ſtands in the Lower <hi>Bretagne</hi> about 82 Miles from
<hi>Rennes,</hi> and 60 from <hi>Breſt,</hi> Long. 14.42. Lat. 47.23. In the
Sea of <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogne</hi> under the 17th Degree of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude there is an
Iſland, which is called <hi>Bell-Iſle,</hi> which extends it ſelf about
21 Miles in Length, 9 in Breadth, and about 54 in Circumference. It is
conſiderable for the Paſſage of Ships along its Coaſts; and for its
ſtrong Caſtle which the Hollanders attak'd in vain <hi>An.</hi> 1674.
notwithſtanding their puiſſant Naval Army for that Effect.
<hi>Oüeſſant,</hi> a little Iſland nearer the Shoar, towards the
Weſt, has the Title of <hi>Marquiſat,</hi> as well as
<hi>Bell-Iſle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29904:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEANOIS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is one of the beſt and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable Countries of
<hi>France,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the moſt extenſive of its Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for it
comprehends Fourteen or Fifteen Provinces or Countries. It is called the
Government of <hi>Orleanois,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Name.</note> becauſe
<hi>Orleans</hi> is the moſt remarkable among the Cities.</p>
               <p>It has near 300 Miles from Eaſt to Weſt,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> from beyond <hi>Chinon</hi>-Caſtle in
<hi>Nivernois,</hi> to the Extremity of <hi>Poiſou;</hi> and near 204 from
South to North, from <hi>Monbrun</hi> in <hi>Angoumois</hi> to
<hi>Nonan-court</hi> in <hi>Normandy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the Eaſt by <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> and
<hi>Champagne;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> in the North by the Iſle
of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Normandy;</hi> in the Weſt by <hi>Bretagne</hi>
and the Sea; and in the South by <hi>Saintonge, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gord, la Marche,</hi> and
<hi>Bourbonnois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soil is very fertile in Corn,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> Wine, Cattle, and in a word, all things that may
conduce to the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Life. Amongſt other Woody parts, it to be
ſeen the Foreſt of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans,</hi> 
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29904:37"/>that contains
70000 Acres; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 'tis ſaid
that in the time of <hi>Francis</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Firſt, it contained 140000. There i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no Country in <hi>France,</hi> where one mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with ſo many Paved Ways as
here.</p>
               <p>It is watered with a great number o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rivers,<note place="margin">Rivers.</note>
amongſt which the <hi>Loire</hi> is the chief. The <hi>Indre,</hi> the
<hi>Cher,</hi> and <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne;</hi> ſwell'd with the Waters of the
<hi>Creuſe,</hi> come to diſcharge themſelves here, between
<hi>Monſoreau</hi> and <hi>Langeſt</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Touraine.</hi> The <hi>Mayne</hi> after
having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the <hi>Loire,</hi> joyned to the <hi>Sarte</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Angers,</hi>
diſcharges it ſelf alſo above this City. The <hi>Charante</hi> takes its
Riſe in <hi>Angoumoy;</hi> which it waters with a part of its Courſe, after
having paſſed in a corner of <hi>Poitou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is obſerved 13 or 14 Countries or principal
Provinces,<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> whereof Four one finds on this
ſide the <hi>Loire,</hi> ſeated in the following order, going from
<hi>Weſt</hi> to <hi>Eaſt, le Maine, le Perch,</hi> the upper
<hi>Beauſſe,</hi> or Country of <hi>Chartres,</hi> and part of
<hi>Gaſtinois.</hi> Five upon the <hi>Loire</hi> in following its Courſe,
<hi>Nivernois, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leanois,</hi> or <hi>Lower Beauſſe; Blaiſois,
Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aine</hi> and <hi>Anjou.</hi> Fore beyond the ſame River, <hi>viz.
Berry, Poitou,</hi> with the Country of <hi>Aunis</hi> and <hi>Angoumois,</hi>
which <pb n="63" facs="tcp:29904:37"/>is yet more advanced towards the <hi>South.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Orleans,</head>
                  <p>SItuated upon the River <hi>Loire,</hi> is the chief City of
this Government. It is very Beautiful, of great Trade, and was heretofore the
Metropolis of a Kingdom that bore its Name. It uſed to be the Reſidence of
Strangers, who were drawn hither by the Magnetick Courteſie of the
Inhabitants, and the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteneſs of the Language they ſpeak here, which is
as highly eſteemed, as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilian is in <hi>Spain;</hi> the Tuſcan in
<hi>Italy:</hi> And as the Attick Tongue was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Grecce.</hi> It
is a Biſhops See, who at his firſt Entrance, has a Priviledge to examine,
and pardon Offenders: Five National Councils have been held here. It has a
Bayliwick, and a very ancient preſidial See; but its Generality is Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern.
It likewiſe has a famous Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. Three memorable Sieges, which it
happily ſuſtained, has made it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned in Hiſtory Under the Title of a
Dutchy, it is the Appennage of the Second Son of <hi>France.</hi> About 68 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29904:38"/>Miles from <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 20.42. Lat. 47.44.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Nevers,</head>
                  <p>FOrmerly called <hi>Noviodunum Adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the Capital of
<hi>Nivernois,</hi> is ſo commodiouſly Situated, that <hi>Julius
Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> choſe it to make a Garriſon of, and a Magazine. It ſhews
no leſs Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in its Churches, than in its Walls; and although it has no
Suburbs, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains notwithſtanding, Eleven Pariſhes: It has a Noble
Caſtle, Ditches full of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a Stone Bridge compoſed of 20 Arches
over the River <hi>Loire,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the <hi>Nievre</hi> in this
place. They have in their Neighbourhood, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of the Medicinal
Waters of <hi>Pougues,</hi> which is a Town where ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parſons go for
the Advantage of their Healths, and where the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Men of
the Province, have built ſtately Houſes for that purpoſe. It has a
Biſhop, and was erected into a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, by <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt. About
30 Miles from <hi>Moulins,</hi> 80 form <hi>Orleans,</hi> and 125 from
<hi>Paris,</hi> Lon. 22.2. Lat. 40.44.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:29904:38"/>
                  <head>Tours.</head>
                  <p>THe City of <hi>Tours,</hi> heretofore
<hi>Caeſaro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunum,</hi> pleaſantly ſeated upon the Loire, the Capital of
<hi>Tourane,</hi> is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, one of the firſt of
<hi>France;</hi> if one conſiders its Situation and its Prerogatives. Under
the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperors it was the Metropolitan of the third <hi>Lyonoiſe</hi> in
<hi>Celtick Gaul:</hi> Its Archbiſhop has for <hi>Suffragans,</hi> the
Biſhop of <hi>Angers,</hi> that of <hi>Mans,</hi> and all thoſe of
<hi>Breſagne.</hi> It has a Generality, a Preſidial, and a Mint. The
Silk-Trade which they drive here, is very advantagious to them. About 48 Miles
from <hi>Poitiers,</hi> 60 from <hi>Orleans,</hi> and 115 from <hi>Rennes</hi>
and <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 19.18. Lat. 47.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Angers,</head>
                  <p>THe Capital City of <hi>Anjou,</hi> ſeated upon the
<hi>Mayenne,</hi> between its Mouth in the <hi>Loire,</hi> and its Confluence
with the <hi>Sarte,</hi> joyned to the <hi>Loire.</hi> It has a conſiderable
Caſtle, and the <pb n="66" facs="tcp:29904:39"/>Houſes covered with which makes it be
called the Black Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> It is
renowned for its Univerſity, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the fine Proceſſion upon <hi>Chriſtmas-day</hi> which every
Year draws many Stran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
to this City. It has a Biſhop und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>A.</hi> of <hi>Tours,</hi> a Bayliwick, a Preſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
and a Mint. About 60 Miles fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Tours,</hi> and nigh 160 from <hi>Paris,</hi> Lon. 17.48. Lat.
47.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Poitiers,</head>
                  <p>THe Capital of <hi>Poitou,</hi> upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Clai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> is one of the largeſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Kingdom; for it yields
to none b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Paris</hi> in
bigneſs. It contains a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Roman Antiquities; 25 Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,
and is adorned with an Epiſcopa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> See under the A. of <hi>Bourdeax;</hi> a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, Mint, and an
Univerſity fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the Civil Law. The Batte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Poitiers</hi> was very unlucky to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> French, and the Engliſh were
doubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Victorious, by the
taking of King <hi>John Charles</hi> the Seventh, King of <hi>France</hi>
transferr'd hither the Parliament of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> which made its
Reſidence here, for the ſpace of 18 Years, during the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh 
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29904:39"/>Wars. About 48 Miles from <hi>Tours,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5 from <hi>Rochelle,</hi>
94 from <hi>Orleans.</hi> Lon.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.00. Lat. 46.34.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Mans,</head>
                  <p>THe Capital City of <hi>Maine,</hi> is moſt agreeably
ſeated upon the <hi>Sarte,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arge, ancient, and very
populous; with the Title of a Biſhoprick, under the A. of <hi>Tours.</hi> It
is obſerved from this City, that the Engliſh laying Siege to it in the Year
1425. firſt put in uſe the great Artillery, which had not as yet been
ſeen in <hi>France.</hi> About 48 Miles from <hi>Tours,</hi> 52 from
<hi>Angers,</hi> and 78 from <hi>Orleans.</hi> Lon. 18.42. Lat. 48.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nogent-le-Rotrou</hi> paſſes for the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of
<hi>Perch,</hi> and yet is but a Burrough-Town, but one of the fineſt
Burroughs of all <hi>France;</hi> and very rich upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of its
Manufacture of Serge, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> About 37 Miles from
<hi>Mans,</hi> as many from <hi>Alenſon,</hi> and 30 from
<hi>Vendôme.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:29904:40"/>
                  <head>Chartres,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Eure,</hi> is the Capital of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſſe, and the Country
of <hi>Chartr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> It once
had its particular Kings, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
has now the Title of a Dutchy, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſerves the Ruins of a Temple bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before the Nativity of Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 'Tis ſaid the City was built
before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deluge, and 'twas
there the Druids <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ciently
Aſſembled. Its Cathedral Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which is a Biſhops See, paſſes for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Ancienteſts of Chriſtendom; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> two Bells whereof are the
fineſt, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> largeſt
in <hi>France.</hi> The Biſhop has mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pariſhes in his Juriſdiction, than any
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ther of the Kingdom. About
42 Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from <hi>Paris,</hi>
and 43 from <hi>Orleans.</hi> Lon. 20.23. Lat. 46.26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Bourges.</head>
                  <p>THis City is the Capital of <hi>Berry Caeſar</hi> ſpeaks
of it as a very ancien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and
powerful City, under the Name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Avaricum Biturigum;</hi> ſeated upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> River <hi>Eure.</hi> It has ſeven great
Gate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:29904:40"/>as
many Suburbs, 17 Pariſhes, and a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reat number of other
Churches. It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onoured
with an Archbiſhoprick, an Univerſity, a Generality, a Bayliwick,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Preſidial See, and a
Mint. Its Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſhop
qualifies himſelf Patriach and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rimat of <hi>Aquitain;</hi>
but that of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eaux</hi> diſputes this Title with him. It
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> about 35 Miles from
<hi>Nevers,</hi> 55 from <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rleans,</hi> and 80 from <hi>Tours,</hi> Lon. 21.14. Lat.
40.55.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Rochelle.</head>
                  <p>THe Country of <hi>Aunis</hi> has nothing recommendable, but
<hi>Rochelle,</hi> which is the Capital thereof. It has an Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal See, a
Preſidial, and a Mint. A City naturally ſtrong, by reaſon of the
Marſhes. But its noble Fortifications are abſolutely reſed. It was often
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, taken and retaken by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and French. But the moſt
memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Siege that ever was laid to it, is that of the Year 1627, where
Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> ordered the Erection of that famous Bank in the Sea,
which has ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as an Admiration to the whole World. The remainders of it
are yet to be ſeen, <pb n="70" facs="tcp:29904:41"/>when the Sea retires. It ſtands on
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ocean, where is an
excellent Bay. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 68 Miles from <hi>Nantes,</hi> 80 fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and 230
from <hi>Paris. Lon.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Lat.</hi> 46.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Angouleme.</head>
                  <p>THe Capital City of <hi>Angomois,</hi> very ancient and
ſtrong, both together <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, erected it into a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy
for his Third Son. This King was Earl of <hi>Angouleme</hi> when he came to the
Crown. The Biſhop ſtiles himſelf Arch-Chaplain to the King, and Baron
<hi>de L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Paine;</hi> which
is a Lordſhip within the City. It has this advantage, as well as
<hi>Poitiers,</hi> that its Mayor and Sheriffs are enobled with their
Deſcendents, by the Priviledges which King <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth has
granted to them. It ſtands on the River <hi>Charente,</hi> 65 Miles from
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelle,</hi> and 210 from <hi>Paris. Lon.</hi> 18.14. <hi>Lat.</hi>
45.46.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:29904:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>BUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GUNDY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is but the Eighth part of the Antient Kingdom of
<hi>Burgundy,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this alone has vulgarly retained
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Name. This Kingdom
compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ended <hi>Savoy,
Suiſſerland,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Zeringhen, Provence, Dauphine,
Lyon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> the Dutchy and County of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> known under the
Name of <hi>Franche-County.</hi> Now there is but Two Provinces that bear the
Name of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> both which are at preſent French Dominions,
<hi>viz.</hi> that which belonged to the Spaniard, which is called
<hi>Franche-County, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Burgundy,</hi> and even <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Burgundy</hi>
by the Germans; and <hi>French Burgundy,</hi> which has born the Title of
<hi>Dutchy,</hi> time out of Mind, and is called the <hi>Royal</hi> and
<hi>Lower Burgundy.</hi> The Name of <hi>Burgundy</hi> proceeds from the
Burgundiones,<note place="margin">Name.</note> a People of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> who
took the place of the antient <hi>Adui,</hi> the ſincere Friends of the
Romans in this Province. Some Etymologiſts make it come from the Town of
<hi>Ougne,</hi> 
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:29904:42"/>which is to be found towards the Source of
the River <hi>Tille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis of the Dutchy, and <hi>la Breſſe</hi> which is annexed
to it, that I deſign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
ſpeak. Its antient Dukes were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly very powerful, and able to
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain long and vigorous Wars againſt their Neighbours. They
poſſeſſed this Province for almoſt Six Hundred Years The laſt was
killed before <hi>Nancy,</hi> in 1477, and left no other Iſſue than a
Daughter, who was Married to <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian,</hi> Arch-Duke of
<hi>Auſtria,</hi> who ſince was Emperor. So <hi>Lewis</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh
King of <hi>France</hi> re-united this Flower to his Crown, as a Maſculine
Fee.</p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf from Eaſt to Weſt above 90 Miles,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> from <hi>Fontaine-Francoiſe,</hi> towards the
<hi>Franche-County,</hi> to <hi>Güaine</hi> in <hi>Auxerrois;</hi> and
about 135 from South to North, from <hi>Semeur</hi> in <hi>Briennois,</hi> to
<hi>Chaleau-Villain</hi> in <hi>Champagne,</hi> without comprehending <hi>la
Breſſe,</hi> which yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances near 30 Miles more towards the South.</p>
               <p>It is bounded in the North by <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne,</hi> in the Eaſt
by <hi>Franche-County,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> and
<hi>Savoy;</hi> in the South by <hi>Dauphine,</hi> and <hi>Lyonncis;</hi> and
in the Weſt by <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonnois,</hi> and <hi>Niverneis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:29904:42"/>
               <p>Its Situation makes it one of the Largeſt, moſt Fruitful,
and moſt Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Province of the Kingdom. The Wines are incomparable,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> and the other Conveniencies of Life are ſo
conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble here, that it is called the Mother of Corn, Wines, and Waters.
There are alſo many pleaſant Woods and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, where there is moſt
excellent Hunting. The delicious Medows, and ſine Paſture-Grounds nouriſh
a ſufficient number of Cattel. Here is to be found ſome Mines of Iron,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt conſiderable of its Rivers is the <hi>Saone;</hi>
the <hi>Yonne</hi> paſſes by <hi>Auxerre;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> the <hi>Ain</hi> through <hi>Breſſe;</hi> the
<hi>Seine, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſon</hi> and <hi>Arroux,</hi> take their Originals from
hence.</p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Dijon,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Ouche,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Capital.</note> is the Capital of the Province. 'Tis a very
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient City, adorned with a Parliament, a Generality, and a Mint; but it has
no Biſhop, and depends upon that of <hi>Langres</hi> in
<hi>Baſſigny,</hi> for the Spirituality. Near this City is to be ſeen the
Village of <hi>Fontanes,</hi> where St. <hi>Bernard</hi> was 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29904:43"/>Born; amongſt the chief Edifices o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Dijon,</hi> they make great account of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Holy Chappel, and
ſeveral Halls, bui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the
time of the Dukes of <hi>Burgundy</hi> for the Lords of the Neighbourhood It is
about 40 Miles from <hi>Autun,</hi> 55 from <hi>Beſanſon,</hi> 146 from
<hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 24.5. Lat. 43.37.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Autun,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Arroux,</hi> is an Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal City, very
antient, and that of all France, which has the fineſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of Antiquity:
It is alſo famous for the Inſtitution of the Order of the Fleece. Its
Biſhop preſides over the States of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> which are held eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Three Years. Near this City <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> overcame the Switzers, who
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to eſtabliſh themſelves in <hi>Gaul,</hi> about 32 Miles from
<hi>Challon,</hi> 50 from <hi>Nevers,</hi> and 145 from <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon.
23.20. Lat. 46.38.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auxerre, Chalon,</hi> and <hi>Maſcon,</hi> are
conſiderable for their Epiſcopal Sees, the firſt renowned for its
excellent Wines.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:29904:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>La Breſſe,</hi> to which I will add the Bayliwick of
<hi>Gex,</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Savoy,</hi> on the Weſt with
<hi>Lyon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> on the North with <hi>Charolois</hi> in the Dutchy of
<hi>Burgundy,</hi> and ſome part of the <hi>Franche-County;</hi> and on the
South with <hi>Dauphine.</hi> The Country is very Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and pleaſant,
embraced between the Rivers <hi>Saone</hi> and <hi>Rhône,</hi> with which
'tis plentifully Watered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Bourg en Breſſe.</head>
                  <p>THE Capital of the whole Province was heretofore a Biſhops
See. Its Cittadel was ſo ſtrong a Fortreſs before it was demoliſhed,
that it was eſteemed little inferior to St. <hi>Katharines</hi> or
<hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meillan</hi> in <hi>Savoy.</hi> The Church of <hi>Brou</hi> is an
Admirable Structure. It contains the Tombs of ſeveral Dukes of
<hi>Savoy;</hi> it ſtands on the River <hi>Reſouſe,</hi> about 34 Miles
from <hi>Lyons,</hi> and 48 from <hi>Geneva.</hi> Lon. 24.31, Lat. 45.54.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:29904:44"/>
                  <head>Bellay,</head>
                  <p>THE Capital of <hi>Bugey,</hi> is a Biſhops See, who
ſtiles himſelf Prince of the Empire, and Temporal Lord of his City. One of
its late Biſhops has been one of the moſt Copious Writers of
<hi>France.</hi> It ſtands on the River <hi>Rhone,</hi> 18 Miles from
<hi>Chambery,</hi> and 40 from <hi>Lyons.</hi> Lon. 25.8. Lat. 45.28.</p>
                  <p>The Principality of <hi>Dombes</hi> lies within the bounds of
<hi>Breſſe.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle <hi>d'Orleans,</hi> to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs,
has coined Mony in the City of <hi>Trevoux,</hi> upon the <hi>Saone,</hi> which
is the Capital thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>LY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONNOIS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEhold the ancient <hi>Celtick Gaul,</hi> or at leaſt the
greateſt part, whereof <hi>M. d'<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rfe,</hi> has ſaid ſo many Wonders in
his Romance of <hi>Aſtraea.</hi> Its Druids, and the exactneſs wherewith
they obſerved here the antient Religion of the <hi>Gauis,</hi> has rendered
it famous in theſe remote
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:29904:44"/>
               <p>One comprehends in this Government <hi>Lyonnois</hi> in
particular, <hi>Beaujolois, Forez, l'Auvergne, la Marche,</hi> and
<hi>Bourbon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf from Eaſt to Weſt,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> about 210 Miles from <hi>Lyons</hi> to the
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of <hi>La Marche,</hi> even beyond the River <hi>Vienne,</hi> and
above 150 from South to North, from the extremity of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergne,</hi> to
<hi>Neron de la Guierche</hi> towards <hi>Berry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the North by <hi>Berry</hi> and
<hi>Nivernois,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> in the Eaſt by
<hi>Breſſe</hi> and <hi>Dauphine,</hi> in the South by <hi>Cevennes,</hi>
and <hi>Rouergue,</hi> and in the Weſt by <hi>Quercy, Limoſin,</hi> and
<hi>Angoumois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soil is not generally Fertile,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> by reaſon of the great Number of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and
Foreſts, which are to be met with in ſome of its Provinces.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rhône,</hi> the <hi>Saone,</hi> the
<hi>Loire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> and the <hi>Allier</hi> are
the moſt celebrated Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that water the extent of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lyonnois</hi> is one of the moſt agreeable Countries of
<hi>France,</hi> being diverſified with Plains and delicious Hills, which
produce very good Corn, excellent Wines, and great ſtore of different 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29904:45"/>Fruits, particularly Cheſnuts, which ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tranſported all over
<hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Lyons,</head>
                  <p>ONE of the moſt ancient and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Cities of
<hi>Gaul,</hi> is a Noble City, ſince its Situation is exceeding pleaſant;
its Climat very Healthful, its Places and Edifices moſt Magnificent. It is at
preſent one of the Richeſt and moſt Populous Cities of the Kingdom, in
Merchants Trading in ſeveral Places by means of the <hi>Loire,</hi> the
<hi>Saone,</hi> and the <hi>Rhône:</hi> There are Banks and
Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondencies for <hi>Africa, Aſia,</hi> and all the principal ſtates
of <hi>Europe,</hi> all ſorts of Manufactures, and Impreſſions of Books,
It was formerly a Colony of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. Its Mayor and Sheriffs are enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
and tranſmit their Honour to their Poſterity. The Canons of the Cathedral
Church are to be Noble in the Fourth Race, and bear the Title of Earls. It has
an Archbiſhop, who qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifies himſelf Primat of the Gauls. There is alſo
a Generality, a Mint, and a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidial See. It is ſeated on the Conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
of the <hi>Rhône,</hi> and the <hi>Saone,</hi> about <pb n="79" facs="tcp:29904:45"/>16 Miles from <hi>Vienne,</hi> 70 from <hi>Geneva,</hi> 150 from
<hi>Turin,</hi> 200 from <hi>Orleans,</hi> and 230 from <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon.
24.8. Lat. 45.24.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Beaujeu,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Ardiere</hi> is the Capital of
<hi>Beaujolois.</hi> There is nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendable in this City, but a very
antient work of Embroidery, which repreſents the Sacrifice of a Hog, a Sheep,
and a Bull, which is to be ſeen over the Portal of the Principal Church. The
Romans called theſe Sacrifices, <hi>Suovetauralia.</hi> It ſtands on the
Brow of a Hill, about 30 Miles from <hi>Lyons,</hi> and 14 from
<hi>Maſcon.</hi> Lon. 23.50. Lat. 45.50.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Mont-Briſon,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Veziſe</hi> paſſes for the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of
<hi>Forez.</hi> It is famous for an Admirable Piece of Clock-work, about 43
Miles from <hi>Lyons.</hi> Lon. 23.10. Lat. 45.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:29904:46"/>
                  <head>Clermont.</head>
                  <p>THis City is not only the Capital o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lower <hi>Auvergne,</hi> but of the whole
Province: It is renowned in Hiſtory for the holding of ſeveral Councils.
Under King <hi>Philip</hi> the Firſt, the Voyage of the Holy Land was here
reſolved on. Here is ſaid to be a Fountain which has the vertue to Petrify,
for with the ſingle courſe of its Waters, which ſeem to be thick and
bituminous; it has made a Wall 200 Yards long, and 4 yards high, with a Bridge,
which they are obliged to cut down ſometimes to prevent its too great
encreaſe. King <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth had the curioſity to go and ſee
it in his Journy to <hi>Bayonne.</hi> It is an Epiſcopal See, and ſtands on
a little Hill about 50 Miles from <hi>Moulins,</hi> 90 from <hi>Lyons,</hi> and
200 from <hi>Paris.</hi> Lon. 22.00. Lat. 45.28.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saint Flour,</hi> is the Capital of Upper
<hi>Auvergne,</hi> remarkable for its Biſhops See, about 45 Miles from
<hi>Clermont.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Riom,</hi> Capital of the Dutchy of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergne,</hi>
holds the Second Rank after <hi>Clermont.</hi> It is adorned with a
Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <pb n="81" facs="tcp:29904:46"/>a Mint, Preſidial, and other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives;
about 7 Miles from <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Moulins.</head>
                  <p>THis City is the Capital of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of
<hi>Bourbonnois,</hi> accompanied with a Caſtle conſiderable for its
ſtrength and building. It has likewiſe very ſine and large Suburbs, where
is made the beſt ſort of Knives and Sciſſars, which are Tranſported
from thence. It has a Generality, upon which depend the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections of
<hi>Montlucon, Gannat</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaon,</hi> and ſome others of
<hi>Nivernois,</hi> and the Upper <hi>Marche.</hi> The Inhabitants have the
reputation of being Civil and Officious. It ſtands nigh the Center of all
<hi>France,</hi> on the River <hi>Allier,</hi> about 28 Miles from
<hi>Nevers,</hi> 96 from <hi>Lyons,</hi> and 90 from <hi>Dijon.</hi> Lon.
22.14. Lat. 46.16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gueret</hi> with its Royal Juriſdictions, is the Capital
of the Upper <hi>Marche,</hi> it ſtands on the River <hi>Cruſe,</hi> about
32 Miles from <hi>Limoges. Dorat</hi> is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of the Lower
<hi>Marche,</hi> about 26 Miles from <hi>Limoges,</hi> and 47 from
<hi>Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:29904:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>GUY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENNE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Country was antiently called the Kingdom of <hi>Aquitain,
ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis,</hi> becauſe of the great number of Springs and Fountains of Hot
Water. <hi>Eleanor,</hi> Inheritrix of this Province, and Wife of
<hi>Loüis</hi> the Young King of <hi>France,</hi> having been Divorced,
eſpouſed <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> to whom ſhe brought for
a Dowry this <hi>Guyenne,</hi> which <hi>Loüis</hi> had rendred to her.
This was a Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand that kindled between the Two Crowns a War, which laſted
near 300 years, and finiſhed but in 1443.</p>
               <p>The Government of <hi>Guyenne</hi> is full as ſpacious as
<hi>Orleanois,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Extent.</note> ſince it extends it
ſelf from Eaſt to Weſt above 240 Miles, from St. <hi>John de
Breüil,</hi> Frontier of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> to the Sea; and from South to
North above 225, from the Port of <hi>Albe</hi> in <hi>Cominge,</hi> to
<hi>Niort</hi> in <hi>Poitou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the North by <hi>Poitou, Angoumois,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> and <hi>la Marche;</hi> in the Eaſt by
<hi>Auvergne,</hi> and <hi>Languedoc;</hi> in the South by the Pyrenaean
Mountains, <pb n="83" facs="tcp:29904:47"/>which ſeparate it from <hi>Spain;</hi> and in
the Weſt by the Ocean.</p>
               <p>The Air is generally wholeſom e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> the Soil fertile in Corn, Wine and Fruits, except
in the Lands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Coaſts, and the Pyrenaeans, where it produces
nothing, but Broom and Paſturage, which feed a good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Cattel.
Fountains of hot Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are generally to be found here.</p>
               <p>It is watered with a great Number of Rivers,<note place="margin">Rivers.</note> amongſt which is remarked the <hi>Garomne,</hi>
the <hi>Lot,</hi> the <hi>Dordonne, l'Adour,</hi> and the <hi>Charnte.</hi> The
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the <hi>Garomne</hi> and the <hi>Dordonne,</hi> which is made at
the Mouth of <hi>Ambez</hi> is very dangerous.</p>
               <p>It is to be obſerved, that from the Mouth of <hi>Ambez</hi> to
the Sea, this River is called <hi>Gironde,</hi> and not <hi>Garomne,</hi> as
<hi>Sanſon</hi> has marked in all his Maps.</p>
               <p>It is divided into two principal Parts, whereof one, that is
towards the North, retains the Name of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> and the other, which
is towards the South, is called in general <hi>Gaſcogne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guyenne</hi> diſtinguiſht into Eight little Countries.
Firſt of all, one obſerves obſerves <hi>Guyenne</hi> (properly ſo
called) and <hi>Bazadois</hi> about the <hi>Garomne; Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois, 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29904:48"/>Quercy,</hi> and <hi>Roüergue,</hi> which are to be
found in order upon the <hi>Lot</hi> in aſcending to its Riſe; on the
Northern ſide, <hi>Limoſin</hi> is ſeated to the North of the
<hi>Dordonne; Perigord,</hi> about the ſame River; and <hi>Xaintogne,</hi>
about the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rente,</hi> and upon the Coaſts of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gaſcogne</hi> is likewiſe divided into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral little
Countries. Firſt, <hi>Armagna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is diſtinguiſhed in the midſt, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelf
to the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Mountains, and is ſubdivided into ſeveral little
Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, as the Upper and Lower <hi>Armagnac,</hi> the Countries of
<hi>Riviere, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dun, Lomagne,</hi> &amp;c. towards the North
<hi>Condommois</hi> and <hi>les Landes,</hi> towards the Weſt, the ſame
<hi>Lands,</hi> and the Land of <hi>Labourd;</hi> on the South, one meets with
in order along the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeans,</hi> the lower <hi>Navarre,</hi> with the
Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>county of <hi>Soul, Bearn</hi> and <hi>Bigorre;</hi> after which one rejoyns
the upper <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magnac;</hi> and towards the Eaſt one
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nds <hi>le Cominge,</hi>
to which may be joyned <hi>le Conſerans.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:29904:48"/>
                  <head>Bourdeaux,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Garomne,</hi> is the Capital of the Government of
<hi>Guyenne,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient, large and beautiful City, wherein is made a
very conſiderable Commerce, by reaſon of the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of its noble
Port. It has all the Qualities, and all the Prerogatives that may render a City
remarkable. It is the See of an Archbiſhop, who qualifies himſelf Primate
of <hi>Aquitaine;</hi> it has a Parliament, a Gonerality, a Mint, an
Univerſity and Admiralty. It is one of the moſt noted Empories of all the
Kingdom, and uſed to be very much frequented by the Dutch and Engliſh for
<hi>Gaſcoign</hi> Wines. About 84 Miles from <hi>Rochelle,</hi> and 120 from
<hi>Toulouſe.</hi> Lon. 17.50. Lat. 44.50.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Agen,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Garomne,</hi> the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of
<hi>Agenois;</hi> holds the firſt Rank after <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and is
ſituated in a Soil, whoſe Fertility makes the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29904:49"/>idle; It is a Biſhops See,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bears the Title of Earl, but
he has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> other Lordly Right in
the City. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lords of
<hi>Exale</hi> deſcended from
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Princes of <hi>Verone</hi>
have had their R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in
<hi>Agen.</hi> About 20 Miles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Condom,</hi> and 35 from <hi>Aux.</hi> Long.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 12. Lat. 44.13.
<hi>Bazas</hi> upon the <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane</hi> is the Capital of <hi>Bazadois,</hi> a ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom City, and ſtands about
25 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> from
<hi>Bourdeaux.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Cahors.</head>
                  <p>THE River <hi>Lot</hi> during its courſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this Province, forms Six or
Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indifferent large
Peninſula's, in one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> which
ſtands <hi>Cahors,</hi> the Capital
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of all <hi>Quercy:
Henry</hi> the Great ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
here ſome Teſtimonies of his Condo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Valour by a Battle, which he o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtinately fought during three days
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ceſſively, to render
himſelf Maſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the City.
Some look upon it as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ancient
<hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xelodunum</hi> which defended
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſelf a long time
againſt <hi>Julius Caeſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d. was born he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> who was called before <hi>James</hi> of
<hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors.</hi> 'Tis a
very ancient City, honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:29904:49"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with an
Epiſcopal See, a Preſidial
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a famous Univerſity; It
has alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Remainders of an
Amphitheatre. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Biſhop takes
upon him the Title of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arl.
Near to <hi>Cahors,</hi> is to be ſeen the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſidue of an Aquaeduct,
which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eretofore above
Nine Miles in Length. About 38 Miles from <hi>Alby,</hi> and 55 from
<hi>Toulouſe.</hi> Lon. 20.6. Lat. 44.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Rhodez,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Aveyron,</hi> is received for the Capital
of all <hi>Roüergue;</hi> It is a very ancient City, but has loſt much
of its Grandeur and Beauty by the Priſals and Repriſals which the
<hi>Goths, Sarrazens</hi> and <hi>French</hi> have made in different times. It
has a Biſhop, and a Preſidial, and ſtands about 48 Miles from
<hi>Mende,</hi> 74 from <hi>Toulouſe,</hi> and 80 from <hi>Narbone.</hi>
Long. 21.20. Lat. 44.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Perigueux,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Lille,</hi> the Capital of
<hi>Perigort,</hi> is more ancient than it is fine, as one may judge by the
Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <pb n="88" facs="tcp:29904:50"/>of an Amphitheatre, which is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be ſeen there, with many
other Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of
Antiquity. In its Neighbou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
hood <hi>Pepin</hi> the Short obtained a ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Victory over <hi>Gayfer</hi> Duke of
<hi>Aquitai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Anno</hi> 768.
It is honoured with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
piſcopal See, and a Preſidial. It is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſweetly ſituated in a pleaſant Valle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> about 42 Miles from
<hi>Limoges,</hi> and 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
from <hi>Bourdeaux.</hi> Longitude 19.18. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude 45.12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Limoges.</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Vienne</hi> is the Capita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of all <hi>Limoſin,</hi> with
a Biſhoprick and a Generality. The City is very populous and rich by reaſon
of it Trade: Its Artiſans are particularly famous for curious Enamel-Work.
'Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a neat, but no large
City, inhabited by a People of ſo great Induſtry, that they compel every
one to work, and is there fore termed by the <hi>French,</hi> the Priſon of
Beggars. At the taking of it, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> revolted, <hi>Edward</hi> the Black Prince could by no means be
allured to pity the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Citizens, till purſuing his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, he
ſaw Three French Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29904:50"/>oppoſe his whole Army; the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of whoſe Courage and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very induced him to Compaſſion,
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before, he had vowed Revenge. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 68 Miles from <hi>Poitiers,</hi>
and 100 from <hi>Bourdeaux.</hi> Lon. 20.00. Lat. 45.40. <hi>Tulles,</hi>
ſeated in a rough and hilly Country, is a Biſhop's See; it ſtands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
33 Miles from <hi>Limoges.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Saintes,</head>
                  <p>BY <hi>Ptolemy</hi> called <hi>Mediolanium,</hi> ſeated upon
the <hi>Charente</hi> is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
the Capital of <hi>Saintonne;</hi> 'tis a very ancient City, and is honoured
with an Epiſcopal See, and a Preſidial. It is about 32 Miles from
<hi>Rochelle,</hi> and 40 from <hi>Angouleſme.</hi> Lon. 17.44. Lat.
45.42.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Aux,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Gez,</hi> anciently called <hi>Auguſta
Auſciorum,</hi> an Archbiſhops See. The Income whereof is ſaid to be
greater, than any Prelates of <hi>France,</hi> reckoned at no leſs than an
Hundred Thouſand Livres <hi>per annum.</hi> It ſtands <pb n="90" facs="tcp:29904:51"/>about 38 Miles from <hi>Toulouſe,</hi> 80 fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and 320 from <hi>Paris.</hi>
Lon. 18.50. Lat. 43.40.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Lectoure.</head>
                  <p>A Biſhops See, called in our Mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Lectodurum,</hi> of old
<hi>Leſtoracium.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
Town ſo well fortified, when in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
poſſeſſion of the Earls of <hi>Armagnac,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it maintained it ſelf three Months againſt
the Strength of <hi>France:</hi> But ſince i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> came into the Power of the French Kings, ſo
ſtrengthened according to the Modern Art of Fortifications, that it
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſteemed the ſtrongeſt
Bulwork of the Kingdom on this ſide, and ſecureſt For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs againſt
<hi>Spain.</hi> It ſtands upon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hill, about 14 Miles from <hi>Condon,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from <hi>Agen,</hi> and 20
from <hi>Aux.</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude 19.4. Latitude 43.58. <hi>Aire</hi> upon the
River <hi>Adour</hi> is an Epiſcopal City, and ſtands about 38 Miles from
<hi>Dax,</hi> and 44 from <hi>Condom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:29904:51"/>
                  <head>Condom,</head>
                  <p>SItuated on the Confluence of the Rivers <hi>Baiſe</hi> and
<hi>Gele,</hi> is the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l of <hi>Condomois.</hi> It is an Epiſcopal City, whoſe laſt
Biſhop has been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledged as a Perſon of an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inary Merit, inſomuch that he
was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hoſen for the
Dauphin's Tutor by the King. It has alſo a Senechalſy, and a Preſidial.
About 20 Miles from <hi>Agen,</hi> and 22 from <hi>Aux.</hi> Long. 18.48. Lat.
44.00. <hi>Dax</hi> and <hi>Bayonne</hi> are alſo Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>op's Sees, ſeated upon the River <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dour,</hi> within 32 Miles of
each other; the former being the Capital of <hi>Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Landes,</hi> the latter of
the Country of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourd.</hi> There is a Mountain near <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onne,</hi>
from whoſe top, 'tis ſaid, one may diſcern three Kingdoms, to wit,
<hi>France, Spain</hi> and <hi>Navarre.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Pau,</head>
                  <p>THE Principality of <hi>Bearn,</hi> is ſituated at the Foot
of the Pyrenees where they joyn to <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and has the 
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29904:52"/>Glory of giving Life to King <hi>Henry</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Great. <hi>Pau</hi> upon the
River <hi>Gave</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
Principal of all the Province, honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> with a Parliament or Court of Judic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ture for all the Country, and a fair P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace built by <hi>Henry</hi> of
<hi>Albret</hi> King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Navarre,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Bearn.</hi> It ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 26 Miles from <hi>Aire,</hi> and 86 from
<hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux.</hi> Lon.
17.40. Lat. 43.23. <hi>Oler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> mounted upon an high Hill, and <hi>Laſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> upon the <hi>Gave</hi>
are alſo Biſhops Sees.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Gathe,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Ardour,</hi> is the Capital of the Earldom
of <hi>Begorre.</hi> It is honoured with a ſtrong Caſtle, and Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal
See, and the Senechalſy for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Country of <hi>Begorre.</hi> It is abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 24. Miles from <hi>Pau,</hi> and 26 from
<hi>Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Lon. 18.14.
Lat. 43.18. Saint <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trand</hi> upon <hi>Garomne,</hi> Capital of <hi>Cominge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> is alſo a Biſhops See,
as is likewiſe Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Lizer</hi> upon the River <hi>Salat,</hi> and <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bez</hi> upon the
<hi>Save;</hi> this laſt but of late erection.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:29904:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>LANGUEDOC.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAEſar</hi> after the Conqueſt of <hi>Provence</hi>
ſtill advances into <hi>Gaul,</hi> diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Province which we call <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Gaul
Narbonoiſe:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the
declining of the Empire, it was
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſurped upon the Romans by
the Goths, who gave it the Name of <hi>Gothia,</hi> eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing therein,
the Kingdom of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigoths, whereof <hi>Toulouſe</hi> was the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal;
and which was abſolutely exting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed ſince <hi>Charles Martel.</hi>
Some Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors pretend, and not without cauſe, that <hi>Languedoc</hi> took
its Denomination from the Goths, who reigning long in the Country, left behind
them a ſmack of their Language, and therefore it was called
<hi>Languegotia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Name.</note> and now <hi>Euphoniae
gratiâ,</hi> termed <hi>Languedotia,</hi> or <hi>Languedoc;</hi> that is,
the Goths Language. <hi>Ortelius</hi> conjectures this to be the reaſon;
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the other French-men in an Affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſay <hi>Oüy,</hi>
theſe of this Country ſay <hi>Oc;</hi> and therefore called
<hi>Languedoc.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Government of <hi>Languedoc,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Extent.</note> which comprehends <hi>les Cevennes,</hi> extends it
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:29904:53"/>ſelf from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> about 210
Mile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And near 240 from
<hi>South</hi> to <hi>North-E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from <hi>Aiqs</hi> in the Earldom of <hi>Foix,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Annonay</hi> towards
<hi>Lyonnois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Rhône</hi> ſeparates it towards th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eaſt</hi> from
<hi>Dauphine</hi> and <hi>Province:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onnis, Auvergne,
Roüergue</hi> and <hi>Quer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> bound it towards the <hi>North: Gaſcog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Armagnac</hi> and
<hi>le Coming</hi> towards the <hi>Weſt;</hi> and <hi>Catalonia,</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea
towards the <hi>Sout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Languedoc</hi> paſſes for one of the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> agreeable and fertile
Provinces of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdom,
having the Advantages o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Olives, Raiſons, Figs, Oranges and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fruits; not ordinary, but here and
in the adjoyning Province.<note place="margin">Quality.</note> The People have
ſomewhat in them of the ancien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goths, and come nearer to the Humon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Spaniards, than any other of the French;
as being eſteemed very devour great Boaſters of themſelves, affecting
Gallantry above their Eſtates; not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how they pinch it on Workydays, or
at home in private. provided they may make a Figure in the Street, and be fine
on Holydays. The Temper of the Women too, but in them 'tis more
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:29904:53"/>
               <p>The Soil of <hi>Cevennes</hi> is very moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inous, and infertile in many places.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n others it poduces Wine,
Millet, Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uts and
other Fruits. Its greateſt Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ility is in Paſturage, which makes the Country abound in Cattel,
eſpecially in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heep and
Mules: Here is a great ſtore of Wildſowl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides the <hi>Rhône,</hi> which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eady mentioned, there are
ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rivers, amongſt which, one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the <hi>Tarn,</hi>
which paſſes by <hi>Montau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an,</hi> and mingles its Waters with thoſe of the
<hi>Garomne</hi> beyond <hi>Moiſſac:</hi> The <hi>Ariege,</hi> the
<hi>Aude</hi> which paſſes by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſſone,</hi> in which the
<hi>Treſquel</hi> diſcharges it ſelf, which is joyned by a <hi>Canal</hi>
with the little <hi>Lers,</hi> which goes to diſcharge it ſelf into the
<hi>Garomne.</hi> 'Tis the <hi>Canal</hi> of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> which has been
ſo much talkt of for the Communication of the two Seas, the <hi>Ocean</hi>
and the <hi>Mideter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean.</hi> Mr. <hi>Du Val</hi> has made a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Map
thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Languedoc</hi> is divided into upper and lower, the one
towards the <hi>Weſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> and the other
towards the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> upon the <hi>Mideterranen</hi> Sea. The firſt
compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends <hi>Toulouſan, Albigeois, Lauragais,</hi> and the Earldom of
<hi>Foix.</hi> The other <pb n="96" facs="tcp:29904:54"/>is diſtinguiſhed into Three
Parts, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Narbonne,
Beziers</hi> and <hi>Niſmes;</hi> which are to be found thus in order, going
from <hi>Weſt</hi> to <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Les Cevennes,</hi> which is ſeated to the <hi>North</hi>
of the <hi>Lower Languedoc,</hi> is alſo diſtinguiſhed into Three
Countries, which are <hi>Gevaudan, Vivarais</hi> and <hi>Vellay.</hi> The
Firſt is towards the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the Second towards the Eaſt, along
the <hi>Rhône,</hi> and the Laſt to the <hi>North</hi> of theſe
Two.</p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Cholouſe.</head>
                  <p>SEated upon the <hi>Garomne,</hi> is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital City of this
Government. It paſſes for one of the ancienteſt, and fineſt Cities of
all <hi>France.</hi> It was the Seat of the ancient Tectoſages, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> made ſo many Conqueſts in
<hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Greece.</hi> It was one of the Colonies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Romans, and ſince that,
Capital of the Kingdom of the Viſigoths; and afterwards that of
<hi>Aquitain,</hi> then of a particular and very powerful County, whoſe
Titular, was Peer of <hi>France.</hi> It is now adorned with an
Archiepiſcopal See, a Parliament, a Seneſchalſey, a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality, a Mint,
and a Univerſity. It <pb n="97" facs="tcp:29904:54"/>enjoys ſeveral Monuments of
Antiquity, as a Capitol, an Amphitheatre, Aque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, ancient Temples, and many
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Curioſities; ſeveral Churches here, and moſt part of the Houſes
are built with Brick. It is about 21 Miles from <hi>Montauban,</hi> 42 from
<hi>Aux,</hi> and 54 from <hi>Chaors.</hi> Lon. 19.48. Lat. 43.29.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Alby,</head>
                  <p>SEated upon the <hi>Tarn,</hi> is the Capital of
<hi>Albigeois.</hi> It was erected but of late to an Archbiſhoprick, by Pope
<hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the Eleventh. Its Archbiſhop is Lord of the City:
Remarkable in Church-Hiſtory, for thoſe great Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites to the
Corruptions and Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> called the
<hi>Albigenſes;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the War was made under <hi>Philip
Auguſtus, Loüis</hi> the Eighth, and <hi>Saint-Loüis.</hi> It
ſtands about 35 Miles from <hi>Rodes,</hi> and 42 from <hi>Toulouſe.</hi>
Lon. 20.40. Lat. 43.43.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Narbon,</head>
                  <p>SEated on the Mouth of the River <hi>Aude,</hi> the firſt
Roman Colony, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Carthage</hi>) out of <hi>Italy.</hi> This
<hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> was in the Infancy of the Roman Empire, the greateſt, and
moſt populous <pb n="98" facs="tcp:29904:55"/>Town of all <hi>France:</hi> Inſomuch
that from it, all this part was called <hi>Galli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Narbonenſis;</hi> a Province, of which
<hi>Plin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> afforded us
this Cenſure, that for Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of Soil, and Civility of People, it was
inferiour to none in the Roman Empire. It had formerly a Capitol, an
Amphitheatre, and ſeveral ancient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents; whoſe Remainders are to be
ſeen at this day. It is an Archbiſhops See, who preſides over the States
of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and is at preſent well Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as a Town of War;
frontiering <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and the Land of <hi>Rouſillon.</hi> It is
about 35 Miles from <hi>Perpignan,</hi> 60 from <hi>Mompelier,</hi> and 88 from
<hi>Toulouſe.</hi> Lon. 21.35. Lat. 42.48.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Nimes.</head>
                  <p>IN Latin <hi>Nemauſus,</hi> anciently a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Colony, now a
Biſhops See; where there remain ſome Marks of the Roman Greatneſs,
eſpecially the Ruins of a ſpacious Palace, built by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror
<hi>Adrian.</hi> It was very much eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Emperors. Between
<hi>Nîmes</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſez,</hi> is to be found the Bridge <hi>du
Gard,</hi> upon the River <hi>Gardon,</hi> which paſſes in this place,
betwixt two Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which are joyned by this Bridge. <pb n="99" facs="tcp:29904:55"/>'Tis one of the nobleſt Monuments that is left us of the Romans. It
has Three Stories of Arches one upon another; and the laſt was an Aqueduct.
Its Structure imprints Horror and Reſpect at the ſame time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nîmes</hi> ſtands about 18 Miles from
<hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> 22 from <hi>Avignon,</hi> and 24 from <hi>Mompelier.</hi> Lon.
22.25. Lat. 43.16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Mompelier.</head>
                  <p>THis City was ſcarce any thing 700 Years ago, but now 'tis
one of the faireſt of <hi>France;</hi> ſeated on a high Mountain, as the
Name imports, ſome 12 Miles diſtant from the Sea. It is honoured with an
Epiſcopal See, a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality, a Mint, a Preſidial, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Univerſity; where Phyſick holds the firſt Rank, and for that very
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſeated; the Country round about affording great variety of Medicinal
Herbs. The Royal Garden of Plants, is a great Curioſity: Of late, one of the
ſtrongeſt Holds, which thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion poſſeſſed
in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and remarkable for the notable Reſiſtance it made
againſt the whole Forces of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, in the laſt
Civil Wars concerning Religion. <pb n="98" facs="tcp:29904:56"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:29904:56"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:29904:57"/>It is about 37
Miles from <hi>Arles, 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> from <hi>Orange,</hi> and 60 from <hi>Narbon.</hi> Lon.
22.52. Lat. 43.8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Le Puy,</head>
                  <p>IS accounted the greateſt City of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc,</hi> after
<hi>Toulouſe.</hi> The Biſhop who ſtiles himſelf Earl of
<hi>Vellay,</hi> where of it is Capital, depends immediately o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Pope, and is ſubordinate
to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Archbiſhop. It ſtands
on the River <hi>Loyre,</hi> about 30 Miles from <hi>Mende,</hi> 56 from
<hi>Viviers,</hi> and 68 from <hi>Lyons.</hi> Lon. 22.58. Lat. 44.33.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mende</hi> and <hi>Viviers,</hi> in the Province of
<hi>les Cevennes,</hi> are remarkable for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their Epiſcopal Sees,
the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops whereof, are ſtiled Earls.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>DAUPHINE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Province, which made part of the ancient Allobroges, was
afterwards compriſed in the Kingdom of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> which
<hi>Charlemagne</hi> joyned to the other Members of <hi>France.</hi> The
Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, being at Variance <pb n="101" facs="tcp:29904:57"/>with
Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh, was ſo perſecuted by his own Children.
that divers Lords taking the Advantage of their Divorce, and deriding him as a
deprived King, carried away each a Piece of this Kingdom. <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o,</hi> Earl of
<hi>Flanders</hi> had <hi>Franche-County: Berald</hi> of <hi>Saxo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> poſſeſſed
himſelf of <hi>Savoy: Provence</hi> fell to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enger,</hi> and
<hi>Dauphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>né</hi> to the Occupation of <hi>Guigue le Gras,</hi> who
gave to it this Name,<note place="margin">Name.</note> upon the account of
<hi>Dauphin</hi> Earl of <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> whoſe Daughter had eſpouſed
his Son.</p>
               <p>It ſhould be incongruous, methinks,<note place="margin">Original
of the Name of <hi>Dauphin.</hi>
                  </note> to intimate here the original of the
Name of <hi>Dauphin,</hi> which has been the Title of the Eldeſt Son of
<hi>France,</hi> for above 300 Years. <hi>Imbert,</hi> or <hi>Humbert,</hi>
Earl <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>Viennois,</hi> having loſt his Son in the faral
Battel of <hi>Crecy,</hi> and unhappily let his laſt Child fall out of a
Window, of which he dyed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf inſulted by
<hi>Amedée</hi> Earl of <hi>Savoy</hi> his irreconcilable Foe, and
find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf unable to reſiſt him, reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to procure him a more
powerful Neighbour. For this effect he offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Country to <hi>Philip</hi>
of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> for him and his 
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:29904:58"/>Succeſſors, upon condition that the Eldeſt Son of
<hi>France</hi> ſhould bear the Title of Dauphin, and that his Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be quartered with
thoſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>France:</hi>
Which Propoſal was accepted of by the King, to the great Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of
the Savoyard: So <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, the Grand-Son of <hi>Philip,</hi>
was the firſt that bore the Name of <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> in the Year 1350.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauphiné</hi> extends it ſelf from Eaſt to
Weſt,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> about 129 Engliſh Miles, from
<hi>Pignerol</hi> to <hi>Valence:</hi> And 111 from North to South, from
<hi>Lanieu</hi> upon the <hi>Rhône</hi> in <hi>Breſſe,</hi> to <hi>le
Buis</hi> in <hi>las-Baron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the North by <hi>Breſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe</hi> and
<hi>Savoy:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> In the Eaſt by
<hi>Piémont:</hi> In the South by <hi>Provence:</hi> And in the Weſt
'tis ſeparated by the <hi>Rhône</hi> from <hi>Languedoc</hi> and
<hi>Lyonnois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soil,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> although very
Mountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, produces excellent Wine, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Corn in ſome Places, as
in thoſe Parts about <hi>Greenoble</hi> and <hi>Die,</hi> and along the
<hi>Rhône;</hi> but in general, it brings forth Rye, Oats, Barley, and a
little Wine. There is one thing here particular enough, in reſpect of a
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is in a
great Rock near <pb n="103" facs="tcp:29904:58"/>
                  <hi>Nions;</hi> There goes out a Wind,
which one is ſcarce ſenſible of when near it; and even boiſterous at 20
or 30 Paces diſtance.</p>
               <p>Its greateſt Rivers are the <hi>Iſere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> which receives the <hi>Drac</hi> below
<hi>Grenoble;</hi> and the <hi>Durance,</hi> which takes its Riſe from hence,
and runs toward <hi>Provence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauphine</hi> is divided into Upper and Lower. The
Firſt,<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> which is towards the Eaſt,
comprehends <hi>Greſivaudan, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ois, lés-Baronies, Gapenſois,
Ambrunois</hi> and <hi>Brianſonois.</hi> The other, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelf
towards the Weſt along the <hi>Rhône,</hi> compriſes <hi>Viennois,
Valentinois,</hi> and <hi>Tricaſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Grenoble.</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Iſere</hi> in <hi>Greſivandan,</hi> is
the Capital City of the whole Country, in Latin, <hi>Gratianopolis,</hi> the
chief Seat heretofore of the <hi>Accuſiani.</hi> 'Tis a very ancient,
populous and well-built City, embelliſhed by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Gratian,</hi>
who gave it its Name: It is much reſorted to by the Nobli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, upon the
account of the Court of parliament erected here in the Year 1453. It has been
an Epiſcopal See <pb n="104" facs="tcp:29904:59"/>for above 1200 Years, and has
beſides, a Generality and a Mint. Equally diſtant, <hi>viz.</hi> abou 30
Miles from <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>né, Die</hi> and <hi>Valence.</hi> Lon. 25.4. Lat.
44.54.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Ambrun.</head>
                  <p>THE Capital of <hi>Ambruncis,</hi> an Arch-Biſhops See,
ſeated upon a very high Rock, in the midſt of a pleaſant Valley,
ſurrounded with Mountains, under which runs the River <hi>Durance.</hi> The
Arch-Aiſhop here, ſhares the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdicton with the King, inſomuch that
their Judges in the Bayliwick, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternative. The hilly Country herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts,
is the higheſt of <hi>France:</hi> About 48 Miles from <hi>Pignerol,</hi> 46
from <hi>Suſa,</hi> &amp;c. Lon. 26.5. Lat. 44.10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Vienne,</head>
                  <p>SEated upon the <hi>Rhône,</hi> is a famous and very
ancient City, as one may ſee by divers Monuments of Antiquity, whoſe
<hi>Veſtigia</hi> are ſtill in being: It is honoured with an
Archiepiſcopal See and a Bayliwick. It had a Bridge over the
<hi>Rhône,</hi> which is broken, <pb n="105" facs="tcp:29904:59"/>and whoſe
Paſſage is very dangrrous for Boats. It is ſituated in the lower
<hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and ſtands about 17 M. from <hi>Lyons.</hi> 43 from
<hi>Grenoble,</hi> and 68 from <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva.</hi> Lon. 14.8. Lat. 45.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Valence,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Rhône,</hi> is a handſome and
populous City, the Capital of <hi>Valentinois:</hi> Its Biſhoprick is united
to that of <hi>Die.</hi> The Biſhop qualifies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Biſhop, and Earl
of <hi>Valence</hi> and <hi>Die,</hi> and the Bayliwick is depending upon this
Prelate. It has given hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Title to two Perſons of more Fame than
Honour: The firſt of which was <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> the Son of Pope
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the Sixth, who was made Duke of <hi>Valentinois</hi> by
<hi>Charles</hi> the Eighht. The other Madam <hi>Diana,</hi> the Miſtreſs
of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, who governed the Affairs of <hi>France</hi> under
him, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the Title of Dutcheſs hereof. About 38 Miles from
<hi>Vienne;</hi> and 43 from <hi>Grenoble.</hi> Lon. 27.12. Lat. 44.32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:29904:60"/>
                  <head>Brianſon,</head>
                  <p>THE Capital of <hi>Brianſonpis,</hi> is ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a
very high Mountain. It is a Biſhops See, and a Bayliwick. It ſtands about
22 Miles from <hi>Ambrun,</hi> and 36 from <hi>Pignerol.</hi> Lon. 26.22. Lat.
44.30. <hi>Saint-Pol-Trois-Châteaux,</hi> is the Capital of
<hi>Tricaſtin.</hi> It is a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing City, ſeated in the lower
<hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiné,</hi> upon an advanced Cliff near the
<hi>Rhône.</hi> It is a Biſhops See, who ſtiles himſelf Earl under
the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi> It ſtands about 16 Miles from
<hi>Orange,</hi> and 72 from <hi>Grenoble.</hi> Lon. 24.2. Lat. 43.53.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Gap,</head>
                  <p>THe Capital of <hi>Gapenſois,</hi> is adorned with an
Epiſcopal See and a Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liwick. Its Biſhop is qualified Earl: It has a very
ſtrong and noble Cittadel. It ſtands about 18 Miles from <hi>Ambrun,</hi>
and 23 from <hi>Siſteron.</hi> Lon. 25.40. Lat. 44.6. <hi>Die</hi> upon the
<hi>Drome,</hi> was an ancient Colony of the Romans, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore the See of a
particular Biſhop, but at preſent joyned to that of <hi>Valence.</hi> It is
ſeated in the lower <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and ſtands about 36 Miles
from <hi>Grenoble.</hi> 
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:29904:60"/>
                     <hi>Le Buis,</hi> upon the
<hi>Aureſe</hi> is the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal City of <hi>les Barronies,</hi> and a
Bayli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Of the Government of <hi>PROVENCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Province made part of <hi>Gaul Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonois,</hi> and was the
Firſt Conqueſt of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Gaul.</hi> He called it the
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by excellency,<note place="margin">Name.</note>
over the other Parts, which he had reduced under the Obedience of the Romans.
It was the Firſt of the ancient Kingdom of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> ſome of
whoſe Kings have born the particular Title of Kings of <hi>Arles,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf from Eaſt to Weſt above 150 Miles,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> from the Mouth of the <hi>Var</hi> to the
<hi>Rhône:</hi> And from South to North, near 120. From the <hi>Cape
Ceerchiez</hi> towards <hi>Toulon,</hi> as far as the <hi>Durance,</hi> 9 Miles
beyond <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the North by <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine;</hi> in the Eaſt,
in part, by <hi>Piemont,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> from which it is
divided by the <hi>Alps</hi> and the County of <hi>Nice;</hi> and in part 
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:29904:61"/>by the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea: In the <hi>South</hi>
by the ſame Sea; and in the <hi>Weſt</hi> by the <hi>Rhône,</hi>
which ſeparates it from <hi>Languedoc.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole is much of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with
<hi>Languedoc,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quality.</note> but is one part thereof;
to wit, between <hi>Marſeilles</hi> and <hi>Arles,</hi> different from all
the reſt of <hi>France.</hi> By the French uſually called <hi>le Crau,</hi>
by the elder Writers, <hi>Campi Lapidei;</hi> becauſe all in a manner,
over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with Stones. In this Province is ſaid to be made the beſt Oyl
of the Kingdom; and very good Salt at <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> and <hi>Pecais.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides the <hi>Rhône,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> one obſerves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt its Rivers, the
<hi>Durance,</hi> which receives the <hi>Verdon,</hi> and the <hi>Hubaye;</hi>
the <hi>Argens,</hi> the <hi>Var,</hi> and the <hi>Arc,</hi> which take their
Original all Three from hence. Here are alſo ſeveral Gulphs, as that of
<hi>Marſeille, Hyeres, Grimaut, Lerins,</hi> &amp;c. Between <hi>la Crau</hi>
and the <hi>Durance,</hi> is to be found Five or Six Lakes. The Mouths or
Channels of the <hi>Rhône,</hi> are called <hi>Graus</hi> in the Language
of the Country. Upon the Coaſts, one meets with the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands of <hi>Martegue, Pomegue, Hyeres,</hi> or
<hi>Stecades;</hi> the Iſles of <hi>Lerins</hi> in their Gulf, which were
heretofore renowned by the Conqueſt, which the late Earl of 
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:29904:61"/>
                  <hi>Harcourt</hi> made here with a handful of Men.</p>
               <p>Although <hi>Provence</hi> is divided into <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
Middle</hi> and <hi>Lower,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> yet it
will be better diſtinguiſhed by its Dioceſſes, which I will endeavour
to put in the eaſieſt order imaginable. Firſt of all, in the
<hi>Middle</hi> one finds the Dioceſſes of <hi>Aix, Riez, Senez</hi> and
<hi>Digne;</hi> the Firſt about the <hi>Durance,</hi> the other Three a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
the <hi>Verdun,</hi> in aſcending to its Spring, which is in the laſt. Upon
the Coaſts, the Dioceſſes of <hi>Arles, Marſeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, Toulon, Trejuls,
Grace</hi> and <hi>Vence;</hi> which are to be met with thus in order, going
from <hi>Weſt</hi> to <hi>Eaſt:</hi> The Dioceſs of <hi>Glandeve</hi> is
about the <hi>Var.</hi> Towards the <hi>North,</hi> thoſe of
<hi>Siſteron,</hi> and <hi>Apt,</hi> with the County of
<hi>Venaiſſin,</hi> with the Principality of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Aix,</head>
                  <p>Near the little River of <hi>Arc,</hi> is the Metropolis of
<hi>Provence,</hi> and was that of <hi>Narbonenſis Secunda,</hi> and at that
time called <hi>Aquae Sextiae,</hi> from <hi>Cajus Sextius;</hi> who brought
hither a Roman Colony, and the Hot Baths here. It is now, and has been of a
long time, an <pb n="110" facs="tcp:29904:62"/>Archbiſhops See, and adorned with a Court
of Parliament for this Country, <hi>An.</hi> 1501. alſo a Generality, and a
Mint. It is a very neat and populous City, memorable in Hiſtory for the great
Defeat of the <hi>Cimbri,</hi> by <hi>C. Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: Eâ victoriâ
viſus meruiſſe, ne ejus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Rempublicam poeniteret;</hi> by this
Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and this alone, obliging the Romans (as <hi>Vellejus</hi> has it) not
to be ſorry for his Birth. About 14 Miles from <hi>Marſeille,</hi> and 36
from <hi>Toulon.</hi> Lon. 24.40. Lat. 43.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Arles,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Rhône,</hi> by <hi>Auſonius,</hi> called
the <hi>Rome</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and in thoſe times ſo highly valued,
that <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Flavius,</hi> being choſen Emperor by the Britiſh
Legions in the declining times of the Weſtern Empire, deſigned to have made
it his Imperial Seat. It is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ancient City, where the Romans
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed their Sixth Colony. It has yet the Remainders of an
Amphithea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, an Obelisk all of Stone, and ſome other Monuments. Its Bridge
of Boats over the <hi>Rhône,</hi> paſſes for a very Noble Work: It
has a low and marſhy Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <pb n="111" facs="tcp:29904:62"/>which natural Strength,
ſeconded by the new Works of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, have made it one
of the moſt aſſured Bulworks of <hi>France,</hi> on this ſide the
Kingdom. It has been the Regal Seat of the French Kings of <hi>Burgundy,</hi>
who from hence were ſtiled Kings of <hi>Arles.</hi> Between this City and the
Sea, but on the other ſide of the River, runs a deep Channel cut with
infinite Charge and Induſtry, by <hi>C. Marius,</hi> for Conveyance of
Victuals into his Camp, in his War againſt the <hi>Cimbri</hi> before
mentioned. It is an Archbiſhops See, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> about 44 Miles from
<hi>Aix,</hi> as many from <hi>Marſeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> and 16 from
<hi>Nîmes.</hi> Lon. 33.38. Lat. 43.5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Marſeille,</head>
                  <p>A Known Port on the <hi>Mideterranean,</hi> and a very ancient
City, which flouriſhed in the time of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> by whom it was
forced, and made a Colony. It was governed as a Republick, and had a famous
Academy. It is an Epiſcopal See, and one of the Admiralty. Its Port
paſſes for one of the ſecureſt of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> See; the
Ships of <hi>France</hi> 
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:29904:63"/>retire hither for the moſh
part; 'tis a place of the greateſt Reſort by the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantins,</hi> and
has a very conſiderable Traffick: For which reaſon it muſt be very
populous. It ſtands about 14 Miles from <hi>Aix,</hi> 38 from
<hi>Toulon,</hi> and 44 from <hi>Arles.</hi> Lon. 24.35. Lat. 42.47.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Coulon,</head>
                  <p>IS alſo an Epiſcopal City, by <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> called
<hi>Tauroentium,</hi> and by ſome, <hi>Tholone;</hi> beautified with a fair
and capacious Haven, one of the beſt of the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> which
ſerves alſo for a Retreat to the French Ships of War, Gallies and many
other Veſſels. It is well ſtored with Oyl, great quantity of Salt
conveyed hither from the Iſle of <hi>Eres,</hi> about 9 Miles off; and a
ſort of Almonds called <hi>Provence</hi> Almonds; made by this means, one of
the moſt frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ports of the <hi>Miditerranean.</hi> About 38 Miles from
<hi>Marſeilles,</hi> 43 from <hi>Aix,</hi> &amp;c. Lon. 25.22. Lat.
42.34.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:29904:63"/>
                  <head>Salon.</head>
                  <p>A Little City, which is renowned for being the Birth-place of
the famous <hi>Noſtradamus,</hi> whoſe Tomb is ſtill to be ſeen here
encloſed in the Wall of the Church, with his Pourtraiture upon it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>Of the County of <hi>VENAI SIN.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Country has been in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of the Holy See, ever
ſince the Year 1228. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth having tranſlated the
Pontifical See to <hi>Avignon</hi> in the Year 1305. <hi>Clement</hi> the
Sixth, purchaſed this City 38 Years after, together with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and his
Succeſſors made their Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reſidence here, to the year 1380. when
<hi>Gregory</hi> the Eleventh, returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:29904:64"/>
                  <head>Avignon,</head>
                  <p>UPon the <hi>Rhône,</hi> is the Capital of the County,
the ordinary Seat of the Popes Vice-Legat, an Archbiſhop, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Inquiſition, and an
Univerſity. In this City are ſaid to be Seven Palaces, Seven
Pariſh-Churches, Seven Monaſteries, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Nunneries, Seven Inns, and Seven
Gates. There is one thing remarkable in Relation to this City, and very
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known by Travellers which is very incommodious about
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vignon.</hi> Namely, that the Gates of this City are exactly ſhut at
Sun-ſet. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any Sububs, or place of Entertainment hereabouts;
no Farmer daring to ſell a Taſte of Wine. It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 16 Miles from
<hi>Orange,</hi> 20 from <hi>Arles,</hi> and 40 from <hi>Aix.</hi> Lon. 23.54.
Lat. 43.22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:29904:64"/>
                  <head>Orange,</head>
                  <p>WIth the Title of Principality is a very ancient City, where
was the Second Colony of the Romans. It is an Epiſcopal See, an Univerſity,
which would by right appertain to King <hi>William</hi> the Third, but now to
the French King. It is famous for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rare Antiquities, Marks of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many
Grandeur, but of moſt note in Church-Hiſtory, for a Council held here
againſt the Semi-Pelagians in the Year, 444, called <hi>Arauſic anum.</hi>
It ſtands on the River <hi>Ligne,</hi> about 47 Miles from <hi>Aix,</hi> 55
from <hi>Mompelier,</hi> and 105 from <hi>Lyons.</hi> Lon. 24.3. Lat.
43.37.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Of <hi>LORRAIN.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Province was the Southern part of the Kingdom of
<hi>Auſtraſy,</hi> whoſe Name it bore, and which <hi>Lotharius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Name.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Son of <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Emperor,
changed into that of <hi>Lother-Reich,</hi> from <pb n="116" facs="tcp:29904:65"/>whence
comes the World <hi>Lorrain: Charles</hi> his yougeſt Brother, thinking that
he had not juſtly dealt with him in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of his Territories,
caſt himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arms of the Emperor, <hi>Otho,</hi> who protected
him againſt <hi>Lotharius,</hi> and gave him the Inveſtiture of
<hi>Lorrain,</hi> with the Title of Duchy upon condition not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,
that it ſhould depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Empire. Thus <hi>Charles</hi> made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<hi>German,</hi> and renounced <hi>France,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which he proceeded
with ſo much Animoſity, that the States of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom looking upon him
not only as a Stranger, but as an odious Enemy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded him from the Crown
after the Death of <hi>Loüis</hi> (called <hi>le Faineant</hi>) his
Nephew, and elected in his place <hi>Hugh-Capet,</hi> Mayor of the Palace, and
Earl of <hi>Paris,</hi> the Chief of the Race of the Preſent Kings.</p>
               <p>It extends it ſelf from the 27th De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree 30 Minutes of
Longitude to the 29th,<note place="margin">Extent.</note> and from the 47th, 30
Min. of Latitude as far as the 49th, 40 Min. inſomuch that it may have from
Eaſt to Weſt about 120 Miles from beyond <hi>Biche</hi> to the River
<hi>Aiſne,</hi> beyond Saint <hi>Menehou;</hi> and near 180 from South to
North, from the Mount of <hi>Forks</hi> to beyond St. <hi>Vendel.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:29904:65"/>
               <p>It is bounded on the North with <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> and the
Dioceſs of <hi>Triers;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> on the Eaſt
with <hi>Alſatia,</hi> and the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate of the <hi>Rhine;</hi> on the
South with <hi>Franche-County;</hi> and with <hi>Champagne</hi> on the
Weſt.</p>
               <p>The Air is temperate enough, the Soil ſufficiently fruitful in
Corn, Wine, Hemp,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> and Paſturage. It affords
alſo divers Metals, as Silver, Copper, Tin, Iron, Lead, and in ſome places
Pearls: Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel and wild-Fowl are alſo very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon here. There are your
Salt-Houſes, which bring a very conſiderable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue. The Rivers abound
with Fiſh, eſpecially with Trouts. The Lake of <hi>Lindre</hi> is ſaid to
be 14 miles in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, which produces wonderful Carps, ſome of them three
Foot long, of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent taſte, and in ſo great qantity, that it has been
farmed at 20000 Livres <hi>per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Rivers of chief note are,<note place="margin">Rivers.</note>
the <hi>Moſa, Muſe</hi> or <hi>Maes,</hi> the <hi>Moſſelle,</hi> the
<hi>Sare,</hi> the <hi>Meurte,</hi> and the <hi>Saone,</hi> which takes its
Original from hence.</p>
               <p>This Seat is divided into two Duchies, to wit, that of
<hi>Lorrain,</hi> and that of <hi>Bar.</hi> The firſt is towards the Eaſt
about the <hi>Moſſelle,</hi> the <hi>Sare,</hi> and the <hi>Meurte;</hi>
the, <pb n="118" facs="tcp:29904:66"/>other is towards the Weſt, about the River
Meuſe.</p>
               <p>The Duchy of <hi>Lorrain</hi> is ſubdivided into three
Bayliwicks, namely, that of <hi>Nancy, Vauge</hi> and <hi>Vaudrevange,</hi>
without comprehending the three Biſhopricks of <hi>Metz, Toul</hi> and
<hi>Verdun,</hi> which don't properly depend upon <hi>Lorrain,</hi> but are
ſtill encloſed within it.</p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Nancy.</head>
                  <p>NEar the River <hi>Meurte</hi> is the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of the
Province. It is not very large, but has a pleaſant and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Situation:
It is divided into the Old and New City; both one and t'other were very well
fortified after the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern way. As ſoon as the King had rendred himſelf
Maſter hereof, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed its Fortifications; but 'tis ſaid, that he
has repaired them ſince, and put them in a much better condition than ever:
It uſed to be the Dukes Seat for the moſt part, and famous for the
Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, which <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> here underwent
with the loſs of his life. It has never a Biſhop; but here is a Primate,
who has the Privilege of <pb n="119" facs="tcp:29904:66"/>wearing a Mitre. It is about 15
Miles from <hi>Toul,</hi> 27 from <hi>Metz,</hi> and 41 from <hi>Verdun.</hi>
Lon. 25.40. Lat. 48.40.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Metz,</head>
                  <p>BY <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> called <hi>Divodurum,</hi> is a very
ancient City ſeated in a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Plain at the Confluence of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<hi>Moſelle,</hi> and <hi>Seille,</hi> well enough for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and commanded
by a good Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel. It was in former times, the Royal Seat of the Kings of
<hi>Auſtraſy,</hi> from hence called Kings of <hi>Metz:</hi> It is a
Biſhop's See, adorned with a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Bayliwick, eſtabliſhed by
the late King <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, 1633. It was once an Imperial
City, but is now ſubject to the French King. It is about 26 Miles from
<hi>Luxembourg,</hi> 34 from <hi>Toul,</hi> and 78 from <hi>Philipsbourg.</hi>
Lon. 25.38. Lat. 49.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Toul,</head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Tullum</hi> of <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> the <hi>Civitas
Leucorum</hi> of <hi>Antoninus,</hi> ſo called from the <hi>Leuci</hi> the
Inhabitants of it, <pb n="120" facs="tcp:29904:67"/>and the Tract about it: It is
pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeated on the <hi>Moſelle,</hi> and anciently honoured with
an Epiſcopal See. It was formerly in the Number of the Imperial Cities of
<hi>Germany,</hi> whoſe! Biſhop is ſtill ſubordinate to the
Archbiſhop of <hi>Trier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> but is now French. It is about 14 Miles from <hi>Nancy,</hi>
and 30 from <hi>Barle-Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Lon. 25.20. Lat. 25.20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Verdun,</head>
                  <p>SEated on the River <hi>Meuſe,</hi> an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Biſhops
See, formerly an Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Town, but now ſubject to the French. The Biſhop
whereof, as alſo thoſe of <hi>Metz</hi> and <hi>Toul,</hi> (being the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ones of this Country of <hi>Lorrain</hi>) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Archbiſhop of
<hi>Triers</hi> for their Metropolitan: All of them hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Imperial
Cities, but taken by <hi>Henry</hi> the Second of <hi>France, Ann.</hi> 1552.
during the Conteſts between <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, and the Proteſtant
Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> under pretence of aiding them againſt the
Emperor. Since that they have been always under the ſubjection of
<hi>France.</hi> It ſtands about 30 Miles from <hi>Metz,</hi> and 41 from
<hi>Nancy.</hi> Lon. 24.48. Lat. <pb n="121" facs="tcp:29904:67"/>49.11.
<hi>Bar-le-Duc,</hi> a neat and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful City, Capital of the Duchy of
<hi>Bar,</hi> ſtands on the River <hi>Ornaon</hi> about 50 Miles from
<hi>Metz.</hi> The late Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> died about three years
ſince, and leſt a Son the preſent Duke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Of the <hi>FRANCHE-COUNTY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Province is a part of the ancient <hi>Cisjurane
Burgundy,</hi> which entred in the dependances of the Houſe of
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> by the means of <hi>Mary,</hi> the Heireſs of
<hi>Burgundy,</hi> and Wife to the Emperor <hi>Maximinian.</hi> The preſent
King of <hi>France,</hi> who never wanted Pretenſions to any thing, when he
found it conſiſtent with his Ambition and Advantage, has taken it twice
even with Expedition. He reſtored it once in favour of a Peace, ſay the
French Geographers; but ſay they, now he keeps it as his Right and
Conqueſt. And to demonſtrate, that it is with Juſtice, purſue they, the
King of <hi>Spain</hi> reſigned it to him by the Peace of <hi>Nimiguen</hi>
in 1679.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:29904:68"/>
               <p>It is ſituated between the 46 and 48th Degree of Latitude, and
extends it ſelf from the 26.20 Min. of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to the 28.20. Min.
inſomuch that it may have from South to North, about 120 Miles from
<hi>Chavannes</hi> to St. <hi>Ann's</hi> Mount nigh the River <hi>Saone,</hi>
and near 90 from Eaſt to Weſt from the River <hi>Doux</hi> near
<hi>Franquemont</hi> in the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Baſle,</hi> to
<hi>French-Fountain</hi> in <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is bounded in the North by <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> by <hi>Suiſſerland</hi> in the Eaſt; in the
South by <hi>Breſſe;</hi> and in the Weſt by the Duchy of
<hi>Burgundy</hi> with <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is very populous and fertile in ſome places,<note place="margin">Quality.</note> where is produced moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Wine, Corn,
and ſtore of Cattle. The Country in ſome parts very Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous; but
thoſe Mountains yield ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Vineyards, and in lieu of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
Barrenneſs, you have an intermix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of moſt delicious and fruitful
Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: There are here, as well as in <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ſome very
conſiderable Salt-Houſes, from whence one City has taken its Name. One
finds herein ſeveral Quarries of black Marble, Jaſper of divers Colours,
and very fine Alabla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:29904:68"/>
               <p>Amongſt the great Number of its Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,<note place="margin">Rivers.</note> is remarked the <hi>Saone,</hi> the <hi>Doux,</hi>
the <hi>Longnon,</hi> and the <hi>Louve,</hi> which are ſtored with
incomparable Fiſh.</p>
               <p>The Province is divided into Three Bayliwicks: That of
<hi>Veſoul</hi> is in the upper part; that of <hi>Dole</hi> in the middle,
and that of <hi>Poligny</hi> is in the lower.</p>
               <div type="town">
                  <head>Dole,</head>
                  <p>UPon the River <hi>Doux,</hi> is the Capital of the whole
Province, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able too for its Riches, Strength, and Beauty. It is very
ancient, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth Emperor fortified it after he had
rebuilt it almoſt entirely new. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly it was an Univerſity for the
Study of the Civil Laws, but now it is devoured, as it were, by a College of
Jeſuits, who have expreſly forbid the People all Proteſtant Books, and
even to talk of God, either in a good, or bad ſenſe: So extreamly fearful
are they, left the Reformed Doctrin ſhould creep in amongſt them. It was
alſo a Parliament City and once, a Baily wick. It is about 30 Miles from
<hi>Dijon,</hi> 34 from <hi>Beſancon,</hi> and 66 from <hi>Geneva.</hi>
Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude 24.44. Latitude 46.54.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="town">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:29904:69"/>
                  <head>Beſancon,</head>
                  <p>UPon the ſame River, is alſo a ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ancient City, called by <hi>Caeſar
Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontio,</hi> then the chief City of the <hi>Sequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> as afterwards
the Capital of the Province called <hi>Maxima Sequanorum;</hi> and an
Archbiſhops See, who ſtiles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Prince of the Empire. The
Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, which have been added to it, make it very ſtrong by Art; and
it Situation between two Mountains, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt encompaſſed by the River
<hi>Doux,</hi> makes it ſo by Nature too. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which was a
<hi>Dole</hi> has lately been transferred hither. About 51 Miles from
<hi>Montbeliard,</hi> 55 Eaſt of <hi>Dijon,</hi> 65 from <hi>Geneva,</hi> and
73 from <hi>Baſil.</hi> Lon. 25.28. Lat. 47.7.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29904:69"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
